<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacobs vvell: or, A sermon preached before the Kings most excellent Maiestie at Saint Albans, in his summer progresse 1612. By William Westerman, Bachelar of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the most Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, his Grace</title>
            <author>Westerman, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839243</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1261:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacobs vvell: or, A sermon preached before the Kings most excellent Maiestie at Saint Albans, in his summer progresse 1612. By William Westerman, Bachelar of Diuinitie, and chaplaine to the most Reuerend Father in God, the Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, his Grace</title>
                  <author>Westerman, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale, for Matthew Lawe, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls churchyard at the signe of the Fox,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through and some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Iacobs VVell:</p>
            <p>Iacobs VVell: <hi>OR,</hi> A SERMON Preached before the <hi>Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie</hi> at Saint <hi>Albans,</hi> in his <hi>summer progreſſe 1612.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM WESTERMAN, Bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of Diuinitie, and Chaplaine to <hi>the moſt Reuerend Father in God,</hi> the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury, his GRACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Beale,</hi> for <hi>Matthew Lawe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop <hi>in Pauls Churchyard at the ſigne</hi> of the Fox. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST <hi>REVEREND</hi> FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE, <hi>by diuine prouidence,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie his Grace, primate of all</hi> England, and Metropolitane, <hi>one of his Maieſties moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> priuie Councell, my verie good Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Reuerend Eather, and my verie honourable good Lord; I will not ſay it was my</hi> happe, <hi>but the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of</hi> God, <hi>and my happineſse, to preach this Sermon, before my dread</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:3"/> Soueraigne, <hi>in his ſummer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe,</hi> at Saint Albans: <hi>where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, that I was an eare-witneſſe of the</hi> wiſdome <hi>of</hi> Salomon, <hi>and a</hi> diuine Oracle, <hi>ſpeaking through his gracious</hi> lippes: <hi>I did alſo experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it to bee true of his</hi> highneſſe, <hi>which was once vttered concerning a</hi> Romane Emperour: <note n="a" place="margin">Qui apud te audent dicere, magnitudinem tuam ignorant: qui nonaudent, bumanitatem. Senec. controu. lib. 7. contr. 8.</note> He that dares ſpeake before him, knowes not his greatneſſe, and hee that dares not ſpeake before him, knowes not his goodneſſe. <hi>For ſuch is his Maieſtie, in Attention, and Attention in Maieſtie, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make the moſt Audacious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and the moſt Timerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. What I then deliuered, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſo</hi> high <hi>a</hi> preſence, <hi>ſo great an Audience, &amp; ſo ample a</hi> Church, <hi>hath left ſuch an</hi> Eccho <hi>behind it, as hath cauſed many to heare the ſound of it, that heard not the voyce it ſelfe: many to report diuerſly of it,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:3"/> 
               <hi>and ſome earneſtly to deſire Copies of the whole</hi> Sermon. <hi>To ſatiſfie all, and to preuent my often trouble, and others miſſ-reporting, who either bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, or worſe it in the rehearſall; I am bold at laſt to commit it to the Preſſe, &amp; to preſent it to your</hi> Grace, <hi>vnder the</hi> banner <hi>of whoſe patronage and encouragement, as of a moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and eminent</hi> Captaine <hi>in the</hi> Iſraell <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>I am preſt, although an vnworthie</hi> Souldier <hi>of</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>to tender the</hi> vtmoſt <hi>of my</hi> ſeruice <hi>toward the benefit of his</hi> Church. <hi>Now as this</hi> Sermon, <hi>at the firſt hearing thereof, receaued a moſt fauourable preiudgement, and acceptance, from the</hi> deepe <hi>wiſdome of</hi> higheſt <hi>Authoritie, for the</hi> worke <hi>ſake, to the which his</hi> Maieſties <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious diſpoſition was ſeltly-inclinable: ſo my truſt is, that your</hi> Graces <hi>great Iudgement and learning, for a</hi> zeale <hi>to the ſame worke, will kindly accept</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:4"/> 
               <hi>of it (how ſmall a peece ſoeuer,) bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the</hi> ſtampe <hi>of his Maieſties ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and let it paſſe for Currant vnder your Graces countenance, with more facile examination, and eaſie Cenſure. Touching the Royall</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>and</hi> promiſe <hi>of his</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>whereby the repaire of the decated</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>is made poſsible, &amp; (I truſt) feazable, leaſt any ſhould</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 6.</note> thinke or ſpeake more then they ſee, or heare in me, <hi>I cannot ſay that I was either</hi> Author, <hi>or any principall</hi> meanes <hi>or Mouer in it, except with the</hi> flye <hi>vpon the</hi> Coach, <hi>I ſhould crie</hi> Ecce quantum pulueris excito: <hi>behold what a duſt I made, when I did nothing to the purpoſe. For who am I firſt; or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> any man; <hi>that</hi> I, <hi>or</hi> they, <hi>ſhould be able to moue the</hi> deepe thoughts <hi>of a</hi> Kings heart; <hi>which by a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcedent peculiar, is in</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Prou. 21. 1.</note> manu Dei, in the hand of God, to turne as
<pb facs="tcp:3646:4"/> the riuers of water, and to manage as it pleaſeth him? <hi>Nay further, there can be neither</hi> action, <hi>or</hi> Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will, power, <hi>or</hi> purpoſe <hi>in any man, that is</hi> good <hi>(how little ſoeuer:) but it is to be reputed as</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Omne quod habemus bonum gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtue eſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: ad Cte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipbont.</hi>
               </note> guſtus Domini, <hi>a</hi> guſt of the Lords <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, a</hi> touch <hi>of his</hi> finger, <hi>whoſe prouidence is the firſt</hi> Mouer, <hi>whoſe</hi> Grace <hi>is the</hi> Center, <hi>and whoſe</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>the</hi> Circumference, <hi>betweene which the</hi> lines <hi>of our</hi> liues, <hi>and beſt intendments, when they goe right and ſtreight, are leuelled. And tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the</hi> meanes <hi>or mediating of the</hi> buſineſſe, <hi>I can claime little, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers much more, and yet none</hi> verie <hi>much: for ſuch was the religious</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> propenſion <hi>of his</hi> Maieſties <hi>roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heart, readily prepared, (as our ſweete</hi> Sauiour <hi>ſitting at</hi> Iacobs well) <hi>to</hi> doe good, <hi>that the</hi> humble <hi>petition of his louing ſubiects in</hi> St. Albans, <hi>was but the diſcouerie of a</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:5"/> 
               <hi>deſperate ſore, to a merciful</hi> Phiſitian, <hi>who was more ready to</hi> cure, <hi>then they to</hi> complaine. <hi>Indeed I confeſſe, that the way being made for me to preach at that time, by that</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">My Lord of <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hf. &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent.</hi>
               </note> Right Reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Father <hi>then attending his</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>(being alſo an eſpeciall fauorite of the motion) I did as a</hi> blunt whetſtone <hi>perhaps a little ſharpen the</hi> razor, <hi>which had</hi> edge <hi>enough of it ſelfe, and like a</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Horat: Athletaeſuis incitatoribus ſunt fortiorcs, &amp; tamen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or, vt pugnet forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or. Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>weake ſtander by, onely yeeld an</hi> applauſe <hi>and</hi> acclamation <hi>to my</hi> Soueraigne, <hi>as a worthie</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sed ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ille exbortatione a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, non magus ſanè quam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſiſſimi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giles, putrorum acclamatione. Bapl Athanaſ.</hi>
               </note> Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>running on ſo good a race, with ſo</hi> faire <hi>a</hi> courſe. <hi>Since which time how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly his maieſty hath proceeded, how well the whole buſines was ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; prepared for the publike diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch by that worthy Knight &amp;</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Chriſtoph. Parkins.</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Requeſts, <hi>formerly acquainted with</hi> Church-building, <hi>how many</hi> honorable fauorites <hi>haue ſeconded the proceedings, it were ouer lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. But I cannot pretermit the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes
<pb facs="tcp:3646:5"/> of that right honorable</hi> Earl of Northhampton <hi>(ſo much ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning high</hi> Nobilitie, <hi>with</hi> exquiſite learning, <hi>to whom our</hi> Church <hi>and ſtate is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for a</hi> Monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of</hi> eternall Memorie <hi>againſt all traiterous</hi> Romaniſts) <hi>who hath rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approued &amp; improued his godly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>and former promiſe toward the repaire of that</hi> Church, <hi>with a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will</hi> beneuolence, <hi>and firſt-fruit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of double</hi> weight <hi>according to the</hi> Sycle <hi>of the</hi> ſanctuarie, <hi>as a luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie hanſell and example to others, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as the beſt gifts are, with ſpeede and maturitie: ſo much is</hi> S. Albans <hi>beholding to his</hi> honor, <hi>for a ſhort time of his youthfull yeeres there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied. And what worthie aſsiſtance your</hi> Grace <hi>hath afforded toward the effectuall accompliſhment of his</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties <hi>pleaſure, not onely in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in that Religious beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of late for</hi> Prague <hi>in</hi> Bohemia,
<pb facs="tcp:3646:6"/> 
               <hi>all true</hi> Chriſtian <hi>hearts doe ſee and acknowledge to the</hi> glorie of God, <hi>cheerefully contributing to ſuch ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good workes, and bleſſing God for the holie deſires of his</hi> Maieſtie <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the</hi> Goſpell <hi>at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; as alſo for your</hi> Grace, <hi>whoſe vigilancie ſtanding</hi> Centinell <hi>upon the higheſt</hi> watch-tower <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>under</hi> God <hi>and his</hi> Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic <hi>is ready to apprehend all occaſions for the Aduancement of Religion, Charitie, and Learning. Neither are the Religious</hi> purpoſes <hi>of his</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>thus happily ſpringing up in his</hi> royall heart, <hi>ſo carefully ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out by your</hi> Graces <hi>Expedition, but they are anſwerably ſpeeded and paſſed along through the Land, by the moſt</hi> vigilant Prelates. <hi>Eſpecially that</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">My Lord B. of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </note> Right Reuerend Father, <hi>our moſt</hi> worthie Dioceſan, <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caeleſtis tuba. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ.</hi>
               </note> that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly trumpet, <note n="m" place="margin">Eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae Regia: Greg: de Baſilio.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Kingly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of diuine Eloquence, <hi>hath not</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:6"/> 
               <hi>onely excited many our brethren to the diligent</hi> prenſation <hi>of the</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities <hi>of the better ſort, as a</hi> proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous winde breathing forwardnes into them <hi>(that I may uſe his</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors <hi>owne words) according to a truſt repoſed in his</hi> Lordſhippe, <hi>but alſo doth continue a moſt</hi> honorable care, <hi>and cautelous</hi> reſpect <hi>to the faithfull employment of all</hi> Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>made for that</hi> worke <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>ſo happily begun, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nierubs or interruptions, ſaue onely ſuch as may ſerue to make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings more</hi> circumſpect <hi>and</hi> ſound. <hi>Yet if this</hi> worke <hi>ſo well becomming the</hi> Magnificence <hi>of a</hi> Chriſtian King, <note n="n" place="margin">Letters patents.</note> 
               <hi>(as his</hi> Maieſtie <hi>acknowledgeth) and commended by your</hi> Grace <hi>for a</hi> Chriſtian, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, an holy and acceptable work, <hi>ſhould have no</hi> oppoſites, <hi>it were ſeeing the reedifying of</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah 4. 1.</note> the Temple <hi>had many</hi> enemies: <hi>and our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:7"/> age <hi>is not without manie, impugning the good ſucceſſe of ſuch-like</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. <hi>The</hi> Anabaptiſt <hi>cannot but diſtaſt the erecting of</hi> Churches, &amp; houſes <hi>of</hi> Gods <hi>publike</hi> ſeruice, <hi>becauſe he ſtandeth upon his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate</hi> Inſpiration, <hi>and neuer aſpireth higher then a</hi> conuenticle <hi>at the moſt. The</hi> Libertine <hi>who liues at large, cannot but eſteeme the</hi> Church <hi>a</hi> Priſon, <hi>the publike Miniſtery a</hi> Seſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>of Enquirie, where he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe arraigned, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and therefore the</hi> graues <hi>and</hi> Tombes <hi>are as the</hi> ſhadow <hi>of</hi> death, <hi>occaſioning</hi> feare <hi>and</hi> horror <hi>before he comes to</hi> execution. <hi>The</hi> Popiſh Recuſant, <hi>who had wont to make more of the</hi> Cage, <hi>then of the</hi> byrd, <hi>and more of a</hi> materiall Church, <hi>then the ſpirituall</hi> Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>is out of loue with our</hi> houſes <hi>of</hi> prayer, <hi>becauſe therein their</hi> Maſſe-Prieſts, <hi>and</hi> ſtrange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb facs="tcp:3646:7"/> 
               <hi>is</hi> ſilenced, <hi>their</hi> Images <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, their Iewiſh</hi> ſacrifices, <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous</hi> Inuocations, <hi>and</hi> Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>are abandoned. And aboue all theſe, the</hi> Couetous polititian, <hi>cannot chuſe but be a</hi> Church-ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>whoſe</hi> Mammon <hi>is his</hi> God, <hi>whoſe priuate</hi> eſtate <hi>is his</hi> Idoll, <hi>to whom onely hee buildes his</hi> houſe <hi>as a</hi> Temple, <hi>and intends all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: as</hi> Ieremie <hi>ſaith of ſuch like:</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ierem. 22. 14.</note> he buildes himſelfe a wide houſe and large Chambers, hee makes himſelfe faire windowes, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with Cedar, and paints it with vermilion: <hi>but if he ſee anie thing beſtowed on</hi> Gods houſe, <hi>or on the</hi> Miniſtry, <hi>he crieth with the officious</hi> purſe-bearer <hi>in the</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <note n="q" place="margin">Mark. 14. 4.</note> Quorſum haec perditio? To what end is this waſt? A leſſe liuing <hi>would ſuffice, a lighter</hi> Cloke <hi>would ſerue</hi> Iupiter, <hi>and a</hi> leſſe Church <hi>would ſerue the people to</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:8"/> 
               <hi>aſſemble in. Of this ſort are they, that by farre-fetched</hi> Trenches <hi>cloſely carried, doe ſeeke to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and ouerthrow all, as</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſebius de vita co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. lib. 1. c. 46.</hi>
               </note> Licinius <hi>in the dayes of</hi> Conſtantine, <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>afaire pretence (that the ayre with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the</hi> Citie <hi>was more wholſome then the aire within the</hi> Citie <hi>where the</hi> Churches <hi>ſtood) would haue drawne the people</hi> to ſerue God <hi>in</hi> the fields, <hi>that hee might haue</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Cogitans euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ionem Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>s, ibid.</note> 
               <hi>demoliſhed the</hi> Churches <hi>in</hi> the Citie. <hi>Neither are</hi> they <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants onely, as the Romaniſts would haue it, that would pull downe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: but the</hi> Couetous polititian, <hi>whatſoeuer</hi> maske <hi>of</hi> Religion <hi>he putteth on, like an</hi> Atheiſt, <hi>and, worſe then an</hi> heathen, <hi>aymeth at the</hi> ſpoile <hi>of his</hi> God, <hi>if it may ſerue for his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate</hi> Emolument. <hi>For who were they that firſt incroached upon</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuings, <hi>and drew away the tythes and maintenance from the ſecular</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:8"/> 
               <hi>prieſts, and ſo by conſequence from the Miniſterie, under the name of</hi> good men, <hi>and</hi> Religious, <hi>but</hi> Monkes <hi>and</hi> Fryars? <hi>It was</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Wolſey, <hi>who by authoritie from the</hi> Pope, <hi>to ſatiſfie his</hi> Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous <hi>or</hi> Ambitious <hi>deſires, or</hi> both, <hi>did pull downe</hi> ſortie Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>and ranſacked them of their wealth. And as by credible teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, I haue heard it often related, the ſame</hi> Cardinall <hi>being ſometimes</hi> Abbot <hi>of the</hi> Monaſterie <hi>of</hi> Saint Albans, <hi>ſent to the</hi> Prior <hi>and</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent <hi>there, that they ſhould conuey up their</hi> plate <hi>to London, ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> maſsiue <hi>and</hi> old, <hi>was growne out of</hi> faſhion, <hi>under colour that he would take order for the new refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming &amp; refyning of that unfaſhiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſiluer, which being ſent vp accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in carts, did ſo waſt in the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting belike that</hi> veſtigia nulla retror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>there came nothing backe againe
<pb facs="tcp:3646:9"/> that euer was heard of. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocuer face the</hi> Papiſts <hi>doe make of</hi> Church building, <hi>yet it ſeemes they preferre pollicy before their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, for every where, ſaith a late</hi> Obſeruant Trauailer <hi>in the</hi> lowe Countries, <note n="t" place="margin">Mr. Ioſeph Hall: dec. 1. ep. 5.</note> Churches fall, and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Colledges riſe; <hi>ſo that not onely the</hi> furie <hi>of</hi> warre <hi>hath ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches, but euen ſuperſtition for aduantage, doth that among ſt them, which couetouſneſſe would faine doe among ſt vs,</hi> robbe God <hi>of his</hi> houſes, <hi>and ſeruice, of his tithes and maintenance. Wherefore the great</hi> Cardinall, <hi>who accuſeth vs, to haue</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Angelis &amp; hominibus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tenentibus omnia &amp; illis delita &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſalutaria Monumenta eripuerunt. Bellar. In pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat: de lib. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit.</note> bereaued both Saints and Angels <hi>in heauen of all</hi> Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments due to them, or heathfull to vs, may a little turne his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint vpon his <hi>owne friends and ſectaries, and tell them of the ſpoile and dilapidations occaſioned in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> and holie <hi>things, by their owne</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:9"/> 
               <hi>couetous and ambitious pollicie. But to leaue their</hi> Ruines, <hi>and come to our preſent building: I finde ſeuerall obiections made, a little hindering the forwardneſſe of wel-diſpoſed people toward a</hi> worke ſo good. <note n="1" place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>Some doubt leaſt their ſhould be ſuperſtition in building up Churches, ſeeing (as they ſay) wee finde neither the name of</hi> Church <hi>in</hi> Scripture, <hi>nor the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Churches</hi> commanded. <note n="2" place="margin">2.</note> 
               <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers finde fault that an Abby Church ſhould be reedified.</hi> 
               <note n="3" place="margin">3.</note> 
               <hi>Some are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the</hi> greatneſſe <hi>of it, becauſe a leſſe would ſerue the people.</hi> 
               <note n="4" place="margin">4.</note> 
               <hi>And ſome againe ſuſpect the faithfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of the</hi> money <hi>collected. To all which, ſeeing I haue already excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the length of an</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>under your Graces Reformation, I am bold to anſwer.</hi> 
               <note n="1" place="margin">1.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> firſt, <hi>who doubt</hi> ſuperſtition, <hi>and finde no</hi> Scripture <hi>for</hi> Churches, <hi>I would deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that, euen the</hi> Name <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:10"/> 
               <hi>(in our tongue ſignifying</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Church, Ky<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rith, Dom: the Lords houſe Angl. Scott: Ger:</note> Gods houſe,) <hi>is read for the</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. Cor. 11. 18.</note> place of Chriſtian Aſſemblies, <hi>in</hi> St. Paul to the Corinthians: <hi>and the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement <hi>for building and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring ſuch places of prayer is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in that generall</hi> rule: <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 14 26.</note> let all things be done to edifying; <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. Cor. 14. 40.</note> let all things bee done honeſtly and by order: <hi>which muſt needes reſpect the comlines of the</hi> place, <hi>if poſsible to be obtained. And therefore when</hi> ſome <hi>at the firſt erecting of comelie and ſpacious</hi> houſes <hi>of</hi> prayer, <hi>in the time of</hi> Conſtantine <hi>cauilled at their</hi> greatneſſe <hi>and</hi> decencie, <hi>becauſe in perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cution they were more</hi> homely, <hi>the</hi> Gangren Councell <hi>made a</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>againſt ſuch as ſhould affirme, that the</hi> houſes <hi>of God ought to bee</hi> bare <hi>and</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Contemptibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Hieron: Zanch. in prec. 4.</note> contemptible; <hi>for they may be</hi> ſimple <hi>and bare upon occaſion and neceſsitie, but they ought not to be ſo, when there is peace, opportunitie</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:10"/> 
               <hi>and authoritie to illuſtrate them. And whereas it is obiected, that there is no expreſſe and particular charge in</hi> Scripture <hi>for</hi> Churches: <hi>no more there was for</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Hoſpinian: de orig. Templ. ca. 4.</note> Synagogues <hi>in the law, yet they were</hi> builded, <hi>and</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, <hi>by the ſeruants of</hi> God, <hi>and euen by</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 4. 15. 16. Iohn. 18. 20.</note> Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe, <hi>and the</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Aſ 15. 21.</note> Apoſtles, <hi>and they were worthily commended, who did build</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 7. 5.</note> Synagogues, <hi>when the deſtruction of them was much lamented. But to free our ſelues from</hi> ſuſpition <hi>of any Superſtitious conceipt, of materiall</hi> Churches, <hi>we are not ſo inamored of them, as the</hi> Iewes were, <hi>or the</hi> Papiſts are, <hi>who ſuppoſe an inherent</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 74. 8.</note> holineſſe <hi>in their</hi> ſtones <hi>and</hi> orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>that the building of them is</hi> meritorious <hi>to</hi> ſaluation, <hi>expiating murders committed; and that</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate prayers <hi>are</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm: de cultu ſactorum lib 3. cap. 9.</hi>
               </note> bettered, <hi>when they are vttered within a conſecrated</hi> Circle. <hi>we know that</hi> Chriſt Ieſus <hi>is</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:11"/> 
               <hi>our true and</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Chriſius ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licuon Dei Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum. Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius in 2. Reg. 12. ex Tertull.</note> Catholike Temple, <hi>which ſanctifieth our prayers when they are made in him onely; and that through him our</hi> bodies <hi>and</hi> ſoules, <hi>are made Temples of the holy Ghoſt, and whereſoeuer our</hi> Supplications <hi>are offered in</hi> ſpirit and truth, <hi>they are alike acceptable to</hi> God. <hi>For what</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis hi lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des habere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turrant. par: in dedic. Eccl.</hi>
               </note> ſanctitie can there bee in ſtones ſaith Saint Bernard, <hi>much like a</hi> Proteſtant, <hi>but that</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sancta ſunt anima propter inhabitantem ſpiritum Dei in nobis, ſancta ſunt corpora propter ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas: ſacta eſt c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam propter Corpora do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. ibid.</hi>
               </note> the place is made holy by the bodies of Saints there aſſembled, the bodies are ſanctified by the ſoules, and the ſoules by the holie Ghoſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in them. <hi>Neither is Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building a worke of it ſelfe acceptable to</hi> God, <hi>but as it is referred to</hi> his ſeruice, <hi>as it is uſed for the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of</hi> holie men to <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſpinian: de orig: Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor. 6. 6.</hi>
               </note> praiſe God, to pray to him, to heare his word, to adminiſter the ſacraments, and to nouriſh faith and charitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Gods people. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:11"/> Saint Hierome reprooues the vanitie of great buildings, when men haue no care of other dueties and vertues; when they <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad: ad Nepoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Miniſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nulla Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctra. ib.</hi>
               </note> adorne their Churches, and make no good choice of Miniſters, <hi>nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the ſeruice of God how ſleightly that is performed. And Saint</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome <hi>commendeth building of churches upon this condition, that if</hi> a man doe it with other graces and vertues, it <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cum cateris bonis addita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum eſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ſine cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris bonis paſſio eſt ſacularis gloria. clnyſ. oper. imperf. in Matt. 23.</hi>
               </note> is an addition to his other vertues and goodneſſe: but if hee haue care to builde Churches without other good workes, it is but a paſsion ofſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and vaine gloris. <hi>And when they are built with greateſt ſtate, if the</hi> word <hi>of</hi> God <hi>bee ſilenced in them, his ſeruice and ſacraments pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, then with</hi> Saint Halirie; <hi>we affirme that the</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Montes mihi &amp; lacus &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rceres &amp; 10. ragines tutrores ſunt. Hil contr. Auxent.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Church of God is not</hi> bound to faire buildings: <hi>but</hi> mountaines and lakes, priſons and
<pb facs="tcp:3646:12"/> gulphes, <hi>are ſafer then they. Yet with the truth, and right ſeruice of God, which by his great bleſsing</hi> we <hi>enioy, they are</hi> excellent Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, holie <hi>to the</hi> Lord, <hi>and</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles amiable <hi>to all faithfull hearts: and with</hi> St. Auſtin, <hi>we ſay, that</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hodie malibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines qui coua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſi ſieri poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, non eſſeeccleſias vbiillis praedicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur praecepta des, noune &amp; ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtium occiderens, ſi in terra viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent? Auguſt. ſer. 220. de tempore.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſuch as would haue</hi> no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where the Ordinances of God ſhould be preached, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie they would euen kill Chriſt, if they found him againe vpon the earth. 2. <hi>Secondly whereas ſome object that the purpoſe is to reedifie an</hi> Abby Church, <hi>as though it were ſome needeleſſe forlorne</hi> Monument of ſuperſtition; <hi>It is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for this</hi> Church <hi>was reſerued from the ſpoile, purged from the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and purchaſed by the inhabitants, for a</hi> pariſh Church, <hi>ſo created and conſecrated to</hi> Gods diuine ſeruice, <hi>in the time of Reformation, and by the Authoritie of</hi> King Edward the
<pb facs="tcp:3646:12"/> ſixt of bleſſed <hi>memorie, and ſo hath continued, with the frequent reſort of many paſſengers, and a great people inhabiting the towne. 3. But a leſſe</hi> Church <hi>(will ſome ſay) would ſerue the people. It is true, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who ſhold haue the parings &amp; the ſhreds?</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Arbore deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta qutuis colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git ligna.</hi>
               </note> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Trce fals, cuerie one gathereth vp the ſtickes. <hi>Great things by that meanes come to little. When his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie was pleaſed to prouide for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of this Church, hee knew well that a leſſe</hi> coate would haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the little boy in Xenophon, <note place="margin">Xenoph. Cyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pad.</note> 
               <hi>then his owne, and the</hi> greater would haue fitted the bigger; <hi>that a</hi> leſſe Church <hi>would haue ſerued the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple perhaps for fitneſſe, but yet his</hi> high wiſdome <hi>deemed the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a propertie to bee beſt</hi> Iuſtice: <hi>and would haue</hi> Suum cuique, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, <hi>his owne,</hi> were it great or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: <hi>ſuppoſing it to be</hi> et peſſimi ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplinec ſui ſaeculi, a bad example <note place="margin">Traian: apud Plinium,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:13"/> vnbecomming his peaceable and religious gouernement, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>the limme-poling of ſuch ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Monuments, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo neceſſarie for the recourſe of his louing ſubiects, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witneſſe of the firſt entrance of the Chriſtian faith into this Realme, by the blood and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome of Saint</hi> Alban, <hi>being a true ſtorie, although ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſfigured by the fabulous</hi> Additions <hi>of the ſuperſtitious. And laſtly, touching the feare and ſuſpition of the faithfull Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the money collected, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I cannot ſay as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, in the time of King</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoas <hi>ſo peremptorilie,</hi> there neede no account bee taken of the men, to whome the money is deliuered for the workemen, becauſe they deale faithfully: <note place="margin">2 King. 12. 15.</note> 
               <hi>yet it is certaine, that hitherto, they</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3646:13"/> 
               <hi>haue proceeded verie carefully, prouided their materials verie fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallie, and forwarded the worke verie induſtriouſlie, not deſiring to ingroſſe the mony, further then the neceſsitie of the worke requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and ſtill keeping a booke of accompts, therein ready to exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite all their proceedings, to the examination and cenſure of thoſe worthie Knights adioyning, or to any other well-willer to this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who ſhall requeſt it. For the continuance of which faithfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, conſidering howe ſtrong a motiue the vigilant eye, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant caution of the</hi> Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Father, my Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe of London <hi>will bee to the under-takers, I dare promiſe all good dealing; yet if ſtanders-by may doe any good, both I and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue vowed to bee inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into the buſineſſe, and (fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:3646:14"/> anie miſcarriage,) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and clamour againſt the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But I reſt in hope of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Office, wherein I may rather commend their doings, then finde fault. In the meane time, ceaſing to bee further troubleſome to your Grace, I humbly take my leaue, neuer ceaſing to pray, as dutie bindeth mee, for the proſperous &amp; victorious reigne of our dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and his royall iſſue, that the weakeſt in his houſe may bee like</hi> Dauid, <hi>and his houſe a ſure houſe, like</hi> Dauids, <hi>euen like Gods houſe, and as an Angell of the Lord, before the people: And for your Grace, that after manie ſucceſſe-full labours in your paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Charge, by ruling and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Church of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied in this life, inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with comfort of conſcience, outwardlie with double honour,
<pb facs="tcp:3646:14"/> you may receiue an incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crowne of righteouſneſſe and glorie, from that great Shepheard of the Sheepe, Chriſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt humble and dueti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chaplaine William Weſterman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3646:16"/>
            <head>IACOBS VVELL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>IOHN 4. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there was</hi> IACOBS WELL.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>ET it not ſeeme ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd that I reade this ſhort <hi>Chorography,</hi> and briefe <hi>deſcription,</hi> of a matter, in appearance, ſo <hi>ſmall,</hi> before this moſt <hi>Illuſtrious Audience.</hi> Rich treaſure may bee hidden in a <hi>roome</hi> vnlikely, and ſuch a narrow <hi>well</hi> as this, may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord much comfortable. <hi>water.</hi> There was no <hi>pinne</hi> in the Temple
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3646:17"/> of God, but was ſeruiceable to ſome holy vſe: neither is there any <hi>iot</hi> or <hi>tittle</hi> in the ſcripture of <hi>truth,</hi> but is profitable for ſome inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. At <hi>this</hi> fountaine, once the <hi>King of heauen</hi> (vailed in the fleſh of our infirmitie) refreſhed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when he was hungry, wcarie, and thirſtie, although <hi>rich</hi> in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>aboue all:</hi> And let my <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord,</hi> ſo <hi>great a King</hi> vpon the earth, in his dcuotions thirſting after the <hi>water of Life,</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his happie progreſſe, vouchſafe his firſt repoſe, out of this well, by the draught of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſeruant, although his own precious heart, be (like <hi>Solomons)</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. King. 4. 29.</note> 
               <hi>large as the ſands,</hi> and deepe as the <hi>waters</hi> of the <hi>Sea.</hi> In this <hi>well</hi> here ſpoken off, the <hi>Patriarch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> left a memoriall of his Charity and care for ſucceeding ages: and at this <hi>well,</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Iacob</hi> left a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3646:17"/> mirrour of his thirſt, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion and comforting of ſoules. Now to preſerue the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of both, did the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> ſet downe this particular <hi>note,</hi> in his holy <hi>Mappe.</hi> Out of <hi>which,</hi> let me be bold, according to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the words, to obſerue <hi>three</hi> eſpeciall <hi>Occurrences:</hi> Firſt of the <hi>place, There:</hi> Secondly, of a <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the <hi>place, a Well:</hi> Thirdly, of the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>founder</hi> of <hi>it, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob: Iacobs Well. A place of note</hi> for many circumſtances, and this eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, of our bleſſed <hi>Sauiours</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. <hi>A monument,</hi> not <hi>great,</hi> but of good <hi>vſe</hi> and benefit, in thoſe drie countries, <hi>A well, A founder</hi> of much reuerence for his faith, for his workes of pietie, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as alſo for his great Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Iacob. There was Iacobs Welll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe <hi>occurrences</hi> (whereof I purpoſe to ſpeak leaſt)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3646:18"/> 
               <hi>is the ſite</hi> and <hi>Landſhip</hi> of the <hi>place,</hi> modelled, or rather folded vp in this briefe locall demonſtratiue, <hi>There:</hi> but explicated more at large for <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> &amp; <hi>Geographie, before</hi> and <hi>after,</hi> by former circumſtances of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and later of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For firſt the <hi>place is bounded</hi> out, as beeing interiacent between <hi>Iudaea</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile,</hi> in the midway betweene them <hi>both.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>name</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Samaria,</hi> and of the <hi>Citie, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char,</hi> (ſo called <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Maldonat.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Sychem)</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, which was a chiefe <hi>Citie,</hi> ſeated at Mount <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſephus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Garrizim,</hi> where <hi>Iacobs ſonnes</hi> once made their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Maſſacre.</hi> Thirdly, the borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>vicinitie</hi> is laid down, as being neere to the poſſeſſion, <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 34</note> that <hi>Iacob</hi> gaue to his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> which hee <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 33.</note> purchaſed of <hi>Hemor, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chems</hi> father. And laſtly is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the departure of our <hi>ſweet Sauiour</hi> from his own countrimen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3646:18"/> and brethren, this way paſsing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long as his iourney ledde him, and heere as it were <note n="f" place="margin">De torrente <hi>in via bibens. Pſal, 1 10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>drinking of the brooke by the way</hi> for his refection. In whom wee may behold that <hi>propheſie</hi> of <hi>Iacob</hi> made to his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph</hi> more liuely verified, then in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ramus fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunàus iuxta fontem. Gen. 45 22.</hi>
               </note> He <hi>ſhall bee as a fruitfull branch by the Well ſide:</hi> for neuer did <hi>Ioſeph</hi> take perſonall poſſeſsion in this place, but <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 11. 22.</note> 
               <hi>by faith,</hi> or by the <hi>tranſlation of his bones,</hi> and in <hi>his poſteritie:</hi> and <hi>they,</hi> Alas! how often interrupted, and at the laſt exterminated <hi>quite.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as this <hi>place,</hi> euen this <hi>Citie</hi> and Country may be poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at for a <hi>Theater</hi> (I will not ſay of Fortune) but of <hi>Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> in the conuerſion of <hi>State,</hi> and alteration of Religion. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that this was <hi>Iacobs</hi> purchaſe, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> inheritance, by promiſe, by legacie, by prophecie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3646:19"/> confirmed to the faithfull; Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the former ſacking of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning of the ſame by <hi>Iacob</hi> himſelfe, It was firſt <note n="i" place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> fired by that Ambitious bramble <hi>Abimelech,</hi> then the whole Region peruerted by the Caluiſh Religion of <note n="k" place="margin">1. Kin. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> in whoſe defection this Citie was <note n="l" place="margin">1. King. 12. 25</note> ſuddenly built, and as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly left. Then Samaria it ſelfe <note n="m" place="margin">2. Kin. 6.</note> beſieged and famiſhed; and at length all harroſed, diſpcopled, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolated; and being <note n="n" place="margin">2. Kin. 17.</note> replanted with Idolatrous inhabitants fearing not GOD, they were wearied with Lyons: When being better taught, yet at their beſt, as they did feare God, ſo they ſtill worſhipped their Idols, continuing in a confuſed Meſlin of Religion. And this race of <hi>ſirangers, Mongrels,</hi> and <hi>Neuters</hi> remained heere till this approch of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> who now
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3646:19"/> 
               <hi>as a <note n="o" place="margin">Cant2. 2.</note> Lillie amongſt the thornes,</hi> &amp; as the Churches deareſt <hi>ſpouſe:</hi> heere <hi>fedde, and</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Cant. 1. 6.</note> 
               <hi>reſted himſelfe at noone,</hi> thirſting in bodie, but more in ſoule for the ſaluation of mankinde, <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. in hunc locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>petens &amp; promittens bibere,</hi> praying and yet promiſing drinke: <hi>being</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Egens tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam acceptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, &amp; affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, tanquam ſatiaturus. vbi ſupr 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in want as one that would receiue, and flowing ouer as one that would repleniſh others.</hi> But I wrap vp this deſcription of <hi>place</hi> againe, with theſe three briefe notes vpon it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> that there is no <hi>certaintie</hi> of continuall <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> in the moſt ſetled eſtates of the <hi>world,</hi> whereof let <hi>Sichem</hi> and Samaria be pregnant witneſſes. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> that <hi>ſinne</hi> priuiledged, and corruption of <hi>Religion</hi> authoriſed, although but in <hi>policie,</hi> as it was by <hi>Ieroboam</hi> (who knew better) yet is the <hi>bane,</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> of the moſt flouriſhing commonwealths and churches. Laſtly, that neither
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3646:20"/> the <hi>Church of God viſibly,</hi> nor the ſpirit illuminating that <hi>Church</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, is bound to any <hi>place, citie</hi> or <hi>ſea, there</hi> to <hi>reſide</hi> in the <hi>ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of perſons: for <hi>Ioſephs poſſeſsion</hi> was inhabited by <hi>Idolaters,</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Oſc 4. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Bethel</hi> became <hi>Bethauen, Turkes</hi> and <hi>dogges</hi> haue ſurpriſed the <hi>holie land, Antichriſt ſitteth</hi> in the <note n="t" place="margin">2 Theſſal. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God:</hi> where was <hi>light,</hi> there is <hi>darkeneſſe,</hi> where it was <hi>day,</hi> now it is <hi>night,</hi> the faithfull <note n="u" place="margin">Iſai 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Citie</hi> is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>harlot,</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nequie blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatur ſibi dc loco: Barn:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leaſt any ſhould flatter themſelues in the inherent holineſſe of the place.</hi> And thus wee leaue wandring at large about the <hi>place,</hi> and ſettle our ſelues in view of a little Monument in the <hi>place,</hi> where our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour</hi> did vouchſafe to ſit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In this place there was a <hi>well,</hi> or a <hi>ſpring:</hi> for euerie well is a <hi>ſpring,</hi> although cuery <hi>ſpring</hi> be not a <hi>well.</hi> A <hi>Spring</hi> or a fountaine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3646:20"/> may be in <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſuperficie,</hi> eaſie to come by: A <hi>well</hi> is in <hi>profundo,</hi> deepe to be drawne at, and ſo was this. A ſeaſonable <hi>Commoditie</hi> of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vſe, and long Continuance, ſeruing for <hi>Iacobs children,</hi> and their Cattle, although now for ſtrangers. <hi>Water</hi> in a thirſty <hi>Lord</hi> muſt needs bee a benefit of great Conuenieucy, vnknowne to them that haue enough. No greater care had the <hi>Petriarchs</hi> in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things, then to furniſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their people with <hi>water.</hi> Wherefore the <note n="z" place="margin">Geneſ. 26. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Philiſtins</hi> could not ſhew their <hi>ſpight</hi> in any thing ſo much to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> as to <hi>ſtoppe</hi> vp his <hi>wels.</hi> Neither (that wee may ſpeake of later times) did the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Philiſtin</hi> in any thing ſo deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcouer his malice, as when hee ſent <hi>paiſoners</hi> to <hi>intoxicate</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the fountaines and <hi>waters</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Countries</hi> in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3646:21"/> whereof, we may reade, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sleidan: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. 18.</hi>
               </note> how the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Noble men did much complaine.</hi> A <hi>well</hi> therefore, and in ſuch a <hi>place,</hi> was ſurely a benefit much graced by the Concurrency of thoſe foure Circumſtances, whereof the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec. de. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nef. Neceſſaria Vtilia Iucunda Manſura,</hi>
               </note> learned ſpeake: for it was <hi>neceſſarie, profitable, pleaſant,</hi> and <hi>permanent.</hi> What more <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> then <hi>water?</hi> No, not a <hi>friend,</hi> for all the <hi>prouerbe.</hi> Who can liue without it? What, more <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> then ſuch a <hi>well,</hi> in a drie ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Countrie, for them that liue, or dwell, or trauell there? And ſo pleaſant is <hi>water,</hi> that <note n="c" place="margin">Prou. 23. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth good newes out of a farre Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie vnto coole waters</hi> comforting a <hi>thirſtie ſoule.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> and greateſt cauſe that made the Iſraelites to quarrell and mutin with <hi>Moſes,</hi> was for <hi>want,</hi> or for <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> of their <hi>water,</hi> as <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 15. 24</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Marah,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 17. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Maſſah,</hi> and <hi>Meribath</hi> can witneſſe. One
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3646:21"/> and the ſame word, (as the <hi>Learned obſerue,)</hi> in the ſacred <hi>fountaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue</hi> is ſet for an <hi>eye,</hi> and a <hi>ſpring,</hi> which may not vnfitly teach vs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as the <hi>eyes</hi> are neceſſary and beautifull <hi>ſprings,</hi> to grace the <hi>little world</hi> of our <hi>bodies:</hi> ſo fountaines of <hi>water,</hi> are as <hi>eyes</hi> to beautifie and ſolace the <hi>greater world</hi> of the <hi>earth.</hi> Our ſweet Sauiour, who at this <hi>well</hi> asked temporall water, and offered ſpirituall water of <hi>life,</hi> hath promiſed a reward to a <hi>Cuppe of cold water,</hi> giuen in ſeaſon, <hi>for his ſake.</hi> And what is a <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 10. 42.</note> 
               <hi>Cuppe of colde water,</hi> to a <hi>well</hi> of <hi>water?</hi> Yet a well of water is no great thing, neither in it ſelfe, but that as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen ſpeaketh:</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nazian: Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtic.</note> 
               <hi>That little, is not little, when it produceth much.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, <hi>that</hi> which addeth an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouement to the <hi>neceſsity, profit,</hi> and pleaſure of this <hi>well,</hi> is the Continuance and <hi>perennitie</hi> of <hi>it,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3646:22"/> holding out, euen till the time of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> out-laſting ſo many changes, generations, and monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies: and yet ſtill there was <hi>Iacobs well. Monumentum aere perennius:</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hor.</note> A monument more durable then braſſe.</p>
            <p>But <hi>this is</hi> not <hi>all:</hi> wee are yet too ſhallow: And our deare <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> hath taught vs to draw deeper, and fetch our hence more then <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie,</hi> and <hi>vulgar</hi> water: For by this <hi>well</hi> he tooke a fit occaſion to proffer and giue a <hi>taſt</hi> of that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>water of life,</hi> whereof he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is the euer-laſting, and vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted <hi>fountaine.</hi> Wherefore I cannot ſeeme to bring water out of mine owne braine vnto this text, nor from the words thereof to wring out blood, by fotcing them, if following the example of the greateſt Doctor, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, I take occaſion from this <hi>well,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3646:22"/> and this <hi>water</hi> to ſpeake of all the Commodities and Emoluments of mans life, which the <hi>Beneficence</hi> of worthie <hi>men, founders</hi> and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours,</hi> hath bountifully ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med out for the publike <hi>vſe</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>many.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Suruey</hi> of which <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities;</hi> as we paſſe along, becauſe <hi>Monuments</hi> are ſo called, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia <note n="i" place="margin">Auguſtin: Moncns men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> mentem,</hi> monitors of the mind. let me behold by them, <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere &amp; mentem &amp; memorem,</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe the minde and the minde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, how that firſt <hi>ſome Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> on the left hand, are <hi>vaine</hi> and <hi>ſuperfluous;</hi> Secondly, <hi>ſome,</hi> in a degree further, <hi>Impious</hi> and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious;</hi> Thirdly, <hi>ſome,</hi> on the right hand of Contrary nature, <hi>Charitable</hi> and <hi>Religious.</hi> And firſt <hi>vaine Monuments</hi> on the left hand I call them not according to the <hi>vanitie,</hi> wherewith <hi>Salomon</hi> hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3646:23"/> branded all worldly things, for ſo the beſt ofſprings of mans Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry are <hi>vaine:</hi> But <hi>vaine,</hi> I meane <hi>Idle,</hi> without any intended benefit or profit for the wealth of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or the ſeruice of God, onely ſhowing forth mens <hi>pride</hi> or <hi>follie,</hi> the <hi>ſuperfluity of their riches,</hi> and their <hi>ſecuritie.</hi> Of this ſort was <note n="k" place="margin">Geneſ. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Nimrods Babel,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 18</note> 
               <hi>Abſolons pillar,</hi> the <hi>Theaters</hi> and <hi>Pyramides</hi> of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> being but <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Regum pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae otioſa &amp; ſtulta oſlenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio: Plin</hi>
               </note> an <hi>Idle and fooliſh Oſtentation of the waſt money of great Princes.</hi> But not to triflle about thoſe meerely <hi>vaine</hi> and Prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous follies, I come to a more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Suruey:</hi> namely, what vaine profuſion of money and labour hath beene Imploied, <hi>firſt in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>manſions</hi> for the <hi>liuing,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly in <hi>tombes</hi> for the <hi>dead,</hi> Thirdly in <hi>ſuperfluities</hi> about the <hi>houſes</hi> of <hi>prayer,</hi> fourthly in <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of writing.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3646:23"/> And firſt touching <hi>manſions</hi> and <note n="i" place="margin">Vaine Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> dwelling <hi>houſes</hi> for the <hi>liuing,</hi> no doubt they muſt and may be built for <note n="n" place="margin">Arles</note> 
               <hi>neceſsity,</hi> for <hi>pleaſure,</hi> for <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> for ſtate <hi>and ſplendour.</hi> But the <hi>venime</hi> of the <hi>ſpider</hi> makes a <hi>webb</hi> of <hi>little worth,</hi> and the corruption of the builder taints his <hi>worke</hi> with a touch of vanity. May you bee pleaſed to ſee how? Firſt when he layes the foundation in a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous confidence of <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie,</hi> ſuppoſing his <hi>houſe</hi> and <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> ſhall <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> 
               <hi>continue for euer,</hi> and therefore calleth it by his owne <hi>name.</hi> Secondly when he ſituates his houſe, and inlargeth his proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vpon grounds depopulated and incroched vpon, ſo that <note n="p" place="margin">1 King. 21. 2.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs</hi> pleaſureable <hi>garden,</hi> ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth vp <hi>Naboths</hi> heritable <hi>vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> Thirdly, when the morter is tempered with the <hi>ſweate</hi> of poore mens <hi>browes,</hi> and the timber
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3646:24"/> wrought without wages: ſo that the <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abacuk. 2. 11</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſtone</hi> in the <hi>wall crieth,</hi> and the timber ecchoeth out a <hi>woe</hi> to the builder. Fourthly, when all the care and expences run out in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall buildings, and priuate gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, and there is no reſpect of the <note n="r" place="margin">Agge. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>houſe of God lying waſt,</hi> or of the ſtate of Religion either ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or falling. Laſtly when thoſe great houſes, which ſhould be wels and fountaines of Rehefe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duicts of comfort to the <hi>hungrie</hi> and <hi>needie,</hi> ſerue onely as onely <hi>Beacons</hi> on a <hi>hill</hi> to bee leene a farre off, where there is <hi>cold</hi> ſtanding and much waiting, but ſeldome any <hi>fire</hi> or <hi>ſmoke,</hi> except vpon ſome rare and ſtrange occaſions.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>manſions</hi> of the <hi>liuing,</hi> I haſten to the <hi>Tombes</hi> of the <hi>dead:</hi> wherein wee may behold how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſiue and Ambitious <hi>vanitie,</hi> hath alſo ſhewed her ſelfe. Not,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3646:24"/> but that there ought to be a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>care,</hi> euen in ſuch <hi>Monuments:</hi> becauſe they are not onely, <hi>ſolatia,</hi> Comforts, but alſo, <hi>Monita viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> Aduertiſements to the <hi>liuing.</hi> The <hi>man</hi> of <hi>God</hi> had his <hi>Tombe</hi> with the <hi>inſcription</hi> preſerued by <hi>King Ioſias;</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">2 King. 23. 18</note> 
               <hi>Let him alone,</hi> (ſaid the King) <hi>let none remoue his bones.</hi> The <note n="t" place="margin">Acts 2. 29.</note> 
               <hi>ſepulchre</hi> of <hi>King Dauid</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained til S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters daies,</hi> for all the rage and Crueltie of Gods Enemies. Such reſpect there was in the making and keeping of the Memorials of worthie men. Wherefore precious for euer in life and death be the memorie of our bleſſed <hi>Ioſias,</hi> who hath not ſuffered the title, and (as I may ſay by Imitation) the <hi>Manes</hi> of our deceaſed <hi>Deborah,</hi> and late <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Iſrael,</hi> to be defaced, but hath reuiued and preſerued them, as in other laſting <hi>Monuments</hi> of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3646:25"/> high wiſdome and deepe learning, ſo in a <hi>Tombe</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>Princely</hi> worthineſſe of <hi>Queene Elizabeth.</hi> But the vanitie is when men in their life, conceaue an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> of their renowne and fame, not in any <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>vertue,</hi> but in ſuch <hi>after ſhadowes</hi> planting their <hi>heauen;</hi> as the Aegyptians rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their <hi>Pyramides,</hi> called them <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pol: virg: ex Diodor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sempitcrnas domos,</hi> houſes cuerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. Or els when great Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages like <note n="x" place="margin">Iſai. 22. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Shobnah,</hi> (or perhaps <hi>Wolſey)</hi> falſe to <hi>God</hi> and their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,</hi> yet <hi>hewe</hi> out their <hi>Tombes in excelſo,</hi> aloft in the <hi>rocke,</hi> making falſhood and Confederacie with forreine Princes their <hi>Refuge,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a ſcourge ſhould paſſe thorough the land. But the Lord euermore bandie and role ſuch as <hi>bals</hi> out of their <hi>Countrie,</hi> and turne their conceited glorie into deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſhame. Beſides when men ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3646:25"/> in the garniſhment of the <hi>Tombes</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> either madly aduancing the Names and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of <hi>Traitours,</hi> and the vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, as <hi>Becket,</hi> and ſuch like: or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſumptuouſly building vp the <hi>Tombes</hi> of godly mon and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres,</hi> as the <hi>Phariſes</hi> did the <hi>ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres of the Prophets,</hi> and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious world, did this of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Alban,</hi> our <hi>worthy</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Cambden: Fox.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>protomar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> not regarding the <hi>faith</hi> or Imitating the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> but ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adorning, nay adoring them, and offering to their ſhrynes as to Idols, wearing out the <hi>ſtones</hi> with their <hi>knees,</hi> and gracing them with forged miracles. <hi>Forged miracles</hi> I may well ſpeake of in <note place="margin">Fox: 705.</note> this place, for here it was, that thu <hi>Noble Protector Humphrey Duke of Gloceſter</hi> diſcouered a fiction of one that fained himſelfe borne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3646:26"/> blinde, and ſuddenly recouered of his ſight by the helpe of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Alban,</hi> whereat, there was great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and ringing of Bels: But the good <hi>Duke</hi> not ſo credulous as the <hi>vulgar,</hi> queſtioning this mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, made triall of the vanitie of it by propounding the difference of colours, which when the partie, that neuer ſaw any thing before (as he ſaid) could name and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, the Duke found him out for a Counterfeit, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his due puniſhment. Pittie but this worthie <hi>Protector,</hi> lying interred in this Church, for this and many other <hi>good deeds,</hi> ſhould haue his <hi>Tombe</hi> preſerued, and a better <hi>Inſcription</hi> or <hi>Epitaph,</hi> then there is vpon it, for had there been many ſuch <hi>Duke Humpbreds,</hi> a briefe <hi>Regiſter</hi> might haue ſaued the turne for popiſh miracles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> becauſe euer ſince the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3646:26"/> firſt <hi>Chriſtian Martyrs</hi> were ſlaine by their perſecutors, or buried and remembred by the faithfull Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, there hath beene a kinde of <hi>Confinitie</hi> betweene the <hi>Tombes</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and holy men decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the <hi>places of praier:</hi> I next obſerue how <hi>vanitie</hi> creeping into thoſe moſt neceſſarie <hi>monuments,</hi> and <hi>houſes</hi> of <hi>praier</hi> and <hi>Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice,</hi> hath beene, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: Abb: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non vanior quam inſanior,</hi> not ſo much vaine, as plaine madde, in building and guilding the materiall wals and temples, neglecting the true Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of God, and the liuing mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt. I muſt not ſtand to fetch in the manifold Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Fathers, onely let vs a little heare <hi>St. Bernard,</hi> who liued when ſuch things wereſwolne big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, and growne to the greateſt <hi>ruffe. I omit</hi> (ſaith he, and yet hee taxeth them) <note n="b" place="margin">Vbiſupra.</note> 
               <hi>the huge Altitudes</hi> of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3646:27"/> the ſteeples or ſpires, <hi>the Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate longitude of</hi> the Church-bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; the <hi>ſuperfluous latitudes</hi> of the Iles, the <hi>ſumptuous garniſhments,</hi> and <hi>curious paintings, reſembling af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort the ancient rite of the Iewes.</hi> Yet thoſe things hee paſſeth by the more lightlie, becauſe perhaps they might ſerue (in ſome ſort) to the honour of God: But <hi>the</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">In ſacroquid faci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aurum? ex. Perſio.</note> 
               <hi>gold and other corporall ornaments,</hi> and bodily oblectations, hee ſoundly reproueth, queſtioning with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe what fruit theſe vanities might bring, whether <hi>ſtultorum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirationem,</hi> or <hi>ſimplicium oblectatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: the wonderment of fooles, or the delight of Idiots;</hi> or whether <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had perhaps learned of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to ſerue Idols:</hi> But at laſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues, that all that prodigall coſt and waſt, was but <hi>an <note n="d" place="margin">Tali quadam. arte ſpargitur as vt multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eetur: expendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vt augea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: &amp; effuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> copiam paril. ibid.</note> art,</hi> and <hi>a lure</hi> to <hi>get lucre,</hi> and <hi>a baite caſt out to angle for more aboundance.</hi> So
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3646:27"/> whereas Churches ſhould haue beene <hi>wels</hi> of heauenly comfort and <hi>Saluation,</hi> they were turned into <hi>gulphes</hi> and <hi>pits,</hi> ſwallowing vp the <hi>fruit,</hi> and <hi>fat</hi> of the Land, being like Exchaunges and Burſes of Marchandiſe, <hi>dennes of theeues</hi> and lurchers, money-chaungers, doue-ſellers, maſſe-mongers, wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chafferers, worthilie driuen out at laſt by <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrates.</hi> But let mee now bee ſparing in this point, ſeeing theſe Monuments haue beene ſo purged of their <hi>peccant humors,</hi> that they are growne weake in their <hi>vitall parts.</hi> They haue ſo beene <hi>let blood</hi> for their temporall ſuperfluities, that from a <hi>pleuriſie,</hi> they are falne to a <hi>Cachexie,</hi> from a <hi>ſwelling</hi> to a d <hi>ſhriueling</hi> and a <hi>ſhrinking</hi> in the <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">e <hi>Dum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nimis iam putrida membra reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Exceſſit Medicina mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum: Lucan. lib. 2.</hi>
               </note> They had indeed hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bodies <hi>ful-fed</hi> and <hi>pampered,</hi> now behold they are <hi>pined, vix oſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3646:28"/> 
               <hi>haerent,</hi> ſcarce doe the ſtones hang together: neither euer were they ſo <hi>foggie,</hi> but they are now as <hi>gant;</hi> not euer ſo <hi>ſurfetted,</hi> but they are now as <hi>hungrie</hi> and thirſtie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuſtained long penance, in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and want for all their former exceſſe, and hauing indeed regorged, and made reſtitution of more then all. And what hope of tolerable recouery can there be? ſeeing thoſe wels and fountaines of Bountie, that had wont to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow in temporall lands and goods toward the Church for ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; are now in the <hi>neape tide,</hi> at a verie <hi>low ebb,</hi> and running from the Church, when they ſhould further the mainteinance of true Religion. Wherefore I may ceaſe to ſpeake of vaine and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exceſſe in theſe <hi>Monuments</hi> of Gods ſeruice, and rather pleade for ſupplie of their moſt neceſſary
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3646:28"/> ſupportance and continuance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthlie I muſt not forget the laſt, and not the leaſt in conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>vaine monuments,</hi> which are <hi>bookes;</hi> excellent <hi>monuments,</hi> if they be good, moſt pernicious, if bad: Idle and vaine, if they be like thoſe <hi>volumes</hi> either in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie or qualitie, whereof <note n="f" place="margin">Hiſt: ceeleſia lib. 7. ca. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Socrates</hi> maketh mention, <hi>quae ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> doctis ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> indoct is prodeſſent,</hi> which neuer were profitable to the learned nor vnlearned; and yet the Author had intituled them with the name of a <hi>Chriſtian hiſtorie, diuided them into ſome thirtie ſixe bookes, euerie booke hauing many Tomes, neere a Thouſand in all, and the Argument of cuerie Tome, almoſt equalling the Tome it ſelfe.</hi> Of ſuch books, ſurely, there was neither <hi>end</hi> of good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or profit, nor almoſt of ſtynt or meaſure, and therefore moſt vaine and Idle: with which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3646:29"/> I might raunge the Bookes of many, that haue ſtuffed the Chriſtian world, with macula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and waſt paper: onely (as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Maximus</hi> once ſaid) <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. p. Max: pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. ad Elpidi um.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>adle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum defatigationem, to the tiring and wearying of readers.</hi> But in haſt I conclude this point, with this compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>int onely, that it is ſhame and pittie, that the Penne and Print, which ſhould be as <hi>wels</hi> and <hi>fountaines</hi> of <hi>Comfort,</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Torcularia diui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nitus mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrala: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander de ras: Ling.</note> 
               <hi>wine-preſſes</hi> to diſtill the ſweer licour of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Religion, ſhould be made to vent out the <hi>froth</hi> and <hi>foame</hi> of idle wordes, and miſſeim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied braines (that I ſay nothing yet of that poyſon and miſchiefe, which often is diſperſed by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly bookes.) And thus much for vaine monuments.</p>
            <p>But <hi>vaine</hi> &amp; <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> is a degree <note place="margin">2 Impious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> ſhort of <hi>Impious</hi> &amp; ſuperſtitious, or Idolatrous. And yet ſuch Impious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3646:29"/> 
               <hi>Monuments</hi> they are, originally naught in the <hi>egge</hi> and in the <hi>birde,</hi> in the <hi>intent</hi> and <hi>effect,</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented as <hi>ſinkeholes,</hi> and <hi>trappes</hi> of the <hi>Diuell,</hi> wherein God himſelfe had no deſtinated part. For what els were thoſe <hi>nurceries</hi> of <hi>vice,</hi> the <hi>houſes of the Sodomites, Topheth,</hi> and <hi>Hinnon,</hi> the <hi>horſes</hi> of the <hi>Sunne,</hi> the <hi>mount of Corruption,</hi> the <hi>Idols of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> the <hi>groues, altars,</hi> and <hi>hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Abhomination deuoted to falſe Gods and goddeſſes,</hi> or indeed to the <hi>Diuell,</hi> vnder the titles of <hi>Baal, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaroth, Chemoz, Milchom, Iupiter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">i 2 King. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Diana,</hi> and infinite ſuch <hi>gulphes</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> and prouocations to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie? I might here inſert, the <note n="k" place="margin">Agrippa.</note> 
               <hi>ſtewes of Pope</hi> Sixtus; <hi>(Veneris monumenta nefandae,)</hi> together with the filthy bookes written to ſuch purpoſe, as <hi>Incitements of luſt.</hi> I might adde all monuments of writing of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, or hereſies, the <hi>golden le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3646:30"/> 
               <hi>of loud lies, the Turkiſh Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, Vlpians ſeauen bookes,</hi> de tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendis Chriſtianis, <hi>of torturing chriſtians,</hi> the diſcourſes of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing, being as Tutors to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and treaſons, the treatiſes iuſtifying <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> and the helliſh and diuelliſh bookes of <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie and curious Arts,</hi> ſuch as the <note n="l" place="margin">Acts 19. 19</note> 
               <hi>beleeuers burnt at their firſt conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> But I paſſe them ouer with contempt and ſilence, becauſe in thoſe things, the <hi>Diuel</hi> ſeemed to haue vnmaskt himſelfe and <hi>ſhow'd</hi> his <hi>hornes</hi> tothe very affrightment, and execration both of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Ciuill World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt be bolder to inſiſt vpon thoſe Monuments, which <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Reuerend Antiquitie</hi> hath deſtinated either in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, or in the generall vnto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſes, and yet ſuperſtition and Idolatrie hath abuſed and diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3646:30"/> wherein the Diuell hath inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored like an hypocrite to ſitvp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the skirts of <hi>Chriſts roate,</hi> and to plant his Chappell ſo neere, that it might incroch vpon the <hi>houſe of God,</hi> and his <hi>ſeruice.</hi> So ſubtill is the <hi>Diuell,</hi> that as <note n="m" place="margin">Arles de Mundo: ſiue Theoph:</note> 
               <hi>Phydias,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Caruer</hi> did cunningly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his owne countenance in the <hi>ſhield of Minerua,</hi> ſo that it could not be razed <hi>out,</hi> but the <hi>ſhield</hi> it ſelfe muſt be ſpoiled and diſfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: euen ſo more or leſſe in the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>houſes of God,</hi> in the <hi>wels</hi> of ſaluation, in <hi>wals, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, tombes, monaſteries,</hi> yea in common wels and fountaines he hath left an infectious leprofie, and deepe impreſſion of Idolattie and ſuperſtition, being the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of himſelfe, ſuch as hardely can be pulled away or purged, but with great diſcretion and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, leaſt all be <hi>defaced.</hi> No ſuch
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3646:31"/> workemen hath the <hi>Diuell</hi> had in this buſineſſe, as the <hi>Romiſh pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Caruers, writers</hi> and <hi>Enginers.</hi> For by their falſe fingers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceirfull braines hee hath fraught the <note n="n" place="margin">Hoſpiniax: de orig: templorum.</note> 
               <hi>Temples of God,</hi> with <hi>heatheniſh rites,</hi> and <hi>Iewiſh Ceremonies</hi> in their <hi>dedications;</hi> and in their vſe, with tempting and ſeducing <hi>Images,</hi> with <hi>Reliques, Maſses, Altars, holie waters</hi> diſtilled out of their owne Inuentions. They haue <note n="o" place="margin">Ierem. 2. 13.</note> forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken God the <hi>fountaine of liuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> the <note n="p" place="margin">Zech. 13. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſpring ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the houſe of Dauid; for ſinne and for uncleanneſſe,</hi> and they <hi>haue digged pits vnto themſelues, which wil hold no water of ſaluation,</hi> or true ſoule-comfort, in ſelfe-merits, ſaints-merits, in ſupererogations, ſatiſfactions, pardons, indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The pure fountaines of the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures</hi> they haue indeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſlaunder with imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3646:31"/> and obſcurity, and to ſtoppe them vp with traditions, gloſſes, froathie legends, lying fictions, and miracles. The ſacramentall <hi>water</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> being the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of our new birth,</hi> they haue puddled with ſalt, oyle, and ſpittle. The Sacramentall <hi>fountaine of Chriſts body and blood,</hi> they haue ſtuffed with a maſſe of abuſes, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries, Adorations, Eleuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reſeruations; driuing the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people, as <hi>uncleane</hi> beaſts, from the myſticall ſtreame of his blood in the <hi>Cup.</hi> To be ſhort, what ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Order</hi> or <hi>Ordinance</hi> is there, which they haue not ſtained and defiled more or leſſe, with the dung and filth, of their owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, ſuperſtitions, or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries? But praiſe be to God that theſe <hi>Monuments</hi> of greateſt <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> thoſe <hi>wels,</hi> and <hi>fountaines,</hi> of true <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo mudled, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3646:32"/> by thoſe <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> are cleanſed and reſtored to their puritie by the Religious Authoritic of our princely <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and <hi>faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</hi> In regard whereof, I may bid auaunt, all <hi>vaine,</hi> and all <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Corruptions of Idolatrie</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, that we may with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort behold the <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Charitie,</hi> and true <hi>Religion,</hi> graced and protected by the higheſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of pietie and bountie (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) the <hi>Princely Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold then how prouident <note place="margin">3 Monuments of Charitie &amp; Religion.</note> and Ingenious <hi>charitie</hi> hath beene in all prouiſions ſeruing for the benefit, and reliefe of the <hi>people. Shee</hi> like the <hi>good huſwife</hi> wrought <hi>by day;</hi> (by the light of the Goſpel) neither did her <note n="q" place="margin">Prou. 31. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Candle</hi> goe out by <hi>night,</hi> no not in the <hi>night</hi> and <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Religion,</hi> for ſtill ſhee was doing, when her ſight was dimme, and ſaw not the right <hi>end</hi> of hir
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3646:32"/> buſineſſe: By a kind of cuſtome and habit the hands wrought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the faſhion of the firſt <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> although the eyes were out. It was the <hi>Lord,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his pleaſure <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſidon: de vita Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>per ſcientes &amp; neſcientes,</hi> whether men know or not know what they doe, for <note n="r" place="margin">Auguſtin: de vera relig. c. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima ſpecies boni á Dco bonoeſt: The leaſt ſhow of good iſſueth originally from God, that is all good.</hi> Walke then thorough the Circuit of <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> and ye ſhall find plaſters for euery <hi>ſoarc;</hi> here <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> for the ſicke and the lame, there <hi>Almeshou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> for the poore and Impotent: here <hi>ſchooles</hi> for her Children; there <hi>Refectories</hi> for her old folkes: here <hi>workehouſes</hi> for the able, there places of Correction for the Idle: here <hi>trades</hi> for the vnskilfull, there <hi>lawes</hi> and orders for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie: here <hi>Entertainement</hi> for ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, there <hi>high waies</hi> paſſable for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3646:33"/> Trauailers: here <hi>prouiſion</hi> for poore Maids mariages, there <hi>Reliefe</hi> and Comfort for priſoners. Neither am I afraid to ſay, that euen Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in her beſt Intendements, had prouided <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nibil aliud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rant Monachorum Monaſteria quam Collegia in quibus ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſi:</hi> Hier: Zanch: in 4 precept:</note> 
               <hi>Monaſteries</hi> by their firſt Inſtitution for <note n="t" place="margin">Caſaubon: ad cp. Card: per. 37.</note> 
               <hi>ſchooles of ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> &amp; <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſeudomar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi>
               </note> ſhops of <hi>manufactures</hi> and <hi>laborious trades;</hi> howſoeuer abuſed ſince. And ſundry ſuch <hi>Wels</hi> of Comfort, hath the <hi>Charitie of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eobs ſonnes</hi> inuented and left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, teaching vs not to be idle in the day and light of true Religion.</p>
            <p>And yet further behold, how <hi>Religion</hi> vniting <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>Charitie</hi> together, hath not onely prouided for the ſupplie of Temporall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsities, but hath been prouident and exuberant in <hi>wels</hi> and <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> to further her children, and diſperſe and propagate her ſelfe. Behold her <hi>vniuerſities &amp; ſchooles,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:3646:33"/> her <hi>Colledges, libraries, bookes</hi> and <hi>lectures</hi> for the ſonnes of her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, whereby they repleniſhing themſelues, may <hi>water</hi> others. See her <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Oratories</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God, and his ſeruice, by the primitiue intent of Religious <hi>Princes,</hi> howſoeuer prophaned ſometimes by iniurie of time, or by default of people, yet repurged againe by the <hi>fauour</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the higheſt Authoritie, from their corruptions. But aboue all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the pure fountaines of <hi>ſacred ſcriptures,</hi> ſtreamed out by <hi>writing</hi> and <hi>printing,</hi> Religiouſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, faithfully tranſlated, being as <hi>wels</hi> for the <hi>deepe ſence,</hi> and <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> for the <hi>eaſie precepts,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not onely the <note n="*" place="margin">Eraſ. in pſal. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Elephant</hi> may <hi>ſwimme,</hi> but the <hi>ſheepe</hi> may <hi>wade:</hi> whence not only the learned may ſatiſfie their deep deſires, but euen the <hi>wild Aſſes may quench their</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:3646:34"/> 
               <hi>thirſt,</hi> the Ignorant <note n="x" place="margin">Prou. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>increaſe</hi> their knowledge. For thereunto ſerue ſo many gracefull, and laborious Expoſitions, Commentaries, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, precepts of tongues and arts, and exerciſes of an eſtabliſhed Miniſtrie, as <hi>Buckets</hi> prouided to draw vp water out of thoſe <hi>wels</hi> of ſaluation. Beſides I may adde hereunto the wholſome lawes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted for the furtherance of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as alſo thoſe wels of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by <hi>tithes</hi> or otherwiſe, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſuch as miniſter in holy things, howſoeuer vnluckily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in a great part by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pilkinton: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. of Agg: Reinald: ſerm: on Obad.</note> 
               <hi>who robbed pariſhes to feede Idle Monks.</hi> But euen in this caſe, we haue experience of a zealous deſire in our <hi>princely Iacob,</hi> and other truly Religious <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> to reſtore thoſe prouiſions to their priſtinate vſe, if the <hi>Iniquitie of time</hi> did not make ſo ſtrong and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3646:34"/> difficult obſtruction. But theſe, and many like theſe, are the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of <hi>Charitie and Religion,</hi> dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this world as in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note n="z" place="margin">2 Pſ. 84. 6.</note> and <hi>vale</hi> of <hi>Bacah,</hi> by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Benefactors,</hi> and repleniſhed by the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of <hi>God</hi> for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and the benefit of his people; in the founding or furthering, the repairing or reſtoring whereof, they are happie that like <hi>Iacob</hi> haue had hearts to affect, or hands and meanes to effect any good. And thus from the <hi>well,</hi> we are come to the <hi>Authour,</hi> from the <hi>Monument</hi> to the <hi>founder, Iacob: It was I acobs well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The name of the <hi>Patriarch Iacob</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> was reuerenly rehearſed by the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in this <hi>well,</hi> although <hi>they</hi> were ſtrangers to <hi>him,</hi> and to his <hi>faith,</hi> making onelie a benefit of this temporall Commoditie, but none of his example in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3646:35"/> better things. But (which is a greater grace) the <hi>holie Ghoſt</hi> by the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> hath regiſtred him, (as elſe where for <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> his <hi>faith,)</hi> ſo heere for this benefit, bearing <hi>his name: Iacobs well.</hi> So that in this little <hi>Monument</hi> of <hi>Charitie,</hi> liues <hi>Iacob,</hi> as in a <hi>Reuerend Record,</hi> when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great <hi>Mountaines of pray,</hi> and <hi>treaſures of vanitie,</hi> together with their <note n="b" place="margin">Polyd. Verg.</note> 
               <hi>founders name,</hi> are vaniſhed, and lie in the duſt, or if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, they doe but <hi>ſtinke in</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Prou. 10. 7</note> 
               <hi>rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe and Corruption.</hi> Such ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour doe men Religious and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable attaine vnto: according to the Pſalme, <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 112. 6.</note> 
               <hi>They are had in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting remembrance:</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Prou. 10. 7.</note> 
               <hi>their memoriall is bleſſed, as ſaith Salomon.</hi> Workes of <hi>mercie</hi> and <hi>pietie</hi> leaue a long &amp; a ſweet ſauour behind them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when the workes themſelues ſometimes doe ceaſe, yet <hi>Iuſtitia manet in aeternum,</hi> the righteouſnes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3646:35"/> of the Authour is written in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and preſerued in the earth. Contrariwiſe, the builder of <note n="f" place="margin">Geneſ. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> liues in perpetuall diſhonour; he that reedified <hi>Iericho,</hi> was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with a <note n="g" place="margin">Ioſhua 6. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe;</hi> and the like <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>curſe</hi> is vpon thoſe that goe about to build vp the <hi>Romiſh Babilon,</hi> to aduance Idolatrie, or ſet vp falſe Religion. <hi>Ieroboam</hi> is branded for <hi>ever</hi> with this <hi>note,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 16. 26</note> 
               <hi>made Iſrael to ſinne. Iudas</hi> beareth the indelible badge of a <hi>traitour to his Maſter.</hi> And indeed the plots and exploits of miſchief are like <hi>monſtruoſi partus,</hi> miſhapen <hi>birthes of Monſters,</hi> imperfect, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, like <note n="i" place="margin">Rob. Winters dreame in Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tletons houſe.</note> 
               <hi>crooked ſteeples,</hi> and <hi>diſfigured faces</hi> in the dreame of a traitor, full of horror to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors while they liue, and of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie when they are dead. So, ingloriouſly, and in deteſtation liues <hi>Gowrie,</hi> and the <hi>powdered</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3646:36"/> 
               <hi>Traitors,</hi> not as <hi>founders,</hi> but as profeſſed <hi>Confounders,</hi> who like beathniſh <hi>Cannibals,</hi> had vowed <hi>this day of</hi> the <hi>weeke, the Tueſday,</hi> to <note place="margin">Dies Martis</note> bloody <hi>Mars,</hi> (or rather to him that was a murtherer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;) <hi>which day</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in memorie and thankes to <hi>God,</hi> for their fruſtrated Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is our <hi>duplex feſtum,</hi> doublic conſecrated, to the honour of the <hi>Almightie,</hi> the ſauiour of his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.</hi> It was not a <hi>well</hi> of <hi>water</hi> to comfort their Countrie, which they went about to <hi>digge,</hi> but a <hi>Hell</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> to conſume vs all, and make vs like <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Ghomorra.</hi> Neither did the <hi>Traitors</hi> ſing as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Nom. 21. 17</note> 
               <hi>Riſe vp Well, ſing ye unto it;</hi> but rather, they thus whiſpered in their damned <hi>ſpels; Riſe vp Hell,</hi> that <hi>Englands Capitol,</hi> the <hi>Parlament houſe,</hi> where ſo many wholſome <hi>lawes</hi> haue beene concluded,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3646:36"/> might make a <note n="l" place="margin">Feu de foy: my L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſpeech to Gamet.</note> 
               <hi>bone-fire, of Ioy</hi> and <hi>triumph</hi> for <hi>Traitors</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> to ſport themſelues withall. But farre is it from the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob</hi> to digge ſuch <hi>pits</hi> of miſchiefe, to ſeeke for <hi>glorie</hi> in <hi>ſhame, merit</hi> in <hi>murder</hi> and villany, or <hi>heauen</hi> in <hi>hell.</hi> Theſe were bloody <hi>Edomites,</hi> that cried of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 137. 7.</note> 
               <hi>downe with it;</hi> but <hi>they</hi> are the bleſſed race of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult how to <note n="n" place="margin">Amos 7. 2, 5.</note> 
               <hi>raiſe vp Iacob</hi> when he is <hi>little or low:</hi> and that doe <note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 122. 7.</note> 
               <hi>pray for,</hi> and <hi>procure the peace of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and the <hi>proſperitie</hi> of her <hi>wals and palaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And within this <hi>kalender</hi> of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs ſonnes,</hi> I doe not onely inrole the moſt magnificent founders, but alſo the <note n="p" place="margin">Conditores, legiſlatores, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratores, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactores: Sr Fr. Eacons Eſſaies.</note> 
               <hi>makers of lawes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the faith;</hi> m-inteiners of vertue, and benefactors by any good meanes, to any good worke: nay euen <hi>fathers of children well</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3646:37"/> 
               <hi>diſciplined;</hi> for as the <hi>wiſe</hi> man ſaith; <note n="q" place="margin">Eccleſ. 40. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Children and the building of a citie, make a perpetuall Name:</hi> and indeed they are ſtreames much gracing the fountaines <hi>whence,</hi> and comforting the city <hi>where</hi> they flow, if they be kept cleare and vncorrupted. Nor muſt I leaue out the moſt laborious <hi>Authors,</hi> and <hi>Collectors</hi> of the <note n="r" place="margin">Sola<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non norunt haec monumenta mori: Martial. lib. 10,</note> 
               <hi>lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt laſting Monuments in bookes</hi> and neceſſary <hi>writings,</hi> then <hi>which,</hi> the world cannot ſhew morefruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full benefits for all poſteritie. But doe I ſpeake onely of thoſe that doe <hi>build</hi> and <hi>plant, alteri ſeculo;</hi> for the age to come? Doe I not alſo giue them their due honour, and the title of <hi>Benefactors,</hi> who are ready to helpe, and relieue the preſent wants of people in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, making themſelues <hi>hands</hi> to the <hi>helpeleſſe,</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Iob 29. 15.</note> 
               <hi>eyes</hi> to the <hi>blinde; feete</hi> to the <hi>lame?</hi> or doe I thinke
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3646:37"/> it onely charity to build <hi>Hoſpitals,</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> to <hi>raiſe Temples?</hi> nay rather when neceſſitie requireth, it is charitie to <hi>cloth the naked li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtones,</hi> to prouide for the true <hi>temples of God,</hi> to redeeme <hi>poore captiues,</hi> euen with the <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ: de offic. Socrat. biſt. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl: lib. 7. c. 27.</hi>
               </note> treaſures of the <hi>Church.</hi> And further, I doe adde to this <hi>wel-deſeruing</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not onely thoſe that <hi>giue,</hi> but alſo thoſe that <hi>take away;</hi> Such as <note n="*" place="margin">Idem. lib. 5. c. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who <hi>partim dando, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim auferendo, partly by giuing bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, partly by Abridging many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes</hi> and Corruptions, was a <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor</hi> to the Citie. To conclude I proclaime all thoſe happie, that by their <hi>aboundance</hi> haue had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and will to doe much good, or by their <hi>mediocritie</hi> haue had power to doe leſſe good, yet <hi>ſome;</hi> or if ſome of their bare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie and extreme pouerty haue ſtriued to doe much good, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3646:38"/> it hath falne to little, yet I exempt them not. And here might I haue done with this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the founder, but that I perceaue ſome rubbes interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the paſſage of my ſpeech and the charitie of the wel-diſpoſed fit to bee remoued. The firſt is a doubt, that when men haue eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed any <hi>good thing</hi> for poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to leaue behind them, leaſt as <hi>Iacobs well,</hi> is now in the hands of wicked <hi>Samaritans,</hi> to whom <hi>he</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer intended <hi>it,</hi> ſo <hi>their</hi> benefits may ſerue in time for <hi>bad people,</hi> or els be Interuerted, miſſe-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied, and waſted, contrarie to the meaning of the Donors. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this diſquieted <hi>Salomon,</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2. 19.</note> that <hi>he ſhould leaue his trauailes to the man that ſhould be after him,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether he would <hi>bee a wiſe man or a foole;</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">verſe 21.</note> nay <hi>homini otioſo quaeſita dimittit:</hi> a man leaues his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3646:38"/> gettings to a <hi>ſluggard ſometimes,</hi> to a <hi>foole, that hath nothing in his hand.</hi> But if this be <hi>vanitie</hi> to perplexe a mans ſelfe in his priuate ſubſtance for feare to leaue it to an vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>heyre;</hi> how much more is it a folly in publike commodities to be ouercurious, in forethinking, who may in time inherit his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, or abuſe them? It is ſuch a thing, as <hi>Iacob</hi> could not preuent, <hi>nor Salomon</hi> with all his wiſdome; nay the <hi>Lord himſelf,</hi> that foreſeeth all changes, yet made the world, where wicked men and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates ſhould dwel, and continueth his benefits of the <note n="z" place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſunne ſhining,</hi> and <hi>raineraining,</hi> vpon the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>vnrighteous.</hi> It is <hi>his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to bee good to all,</hi> both good and bad, to be rich and bountifull to them that miſſpend his fauors, as well as to others that vſe them well. Let vs learne this perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3646:39"/> and <hi>not be</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 6. 9. 10</note> 
               <hi>wearie of well doing: for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reape, if we faint not: while wee haue time let vs doe good to all men, but eſpecially to them that are of the houſhold of faith.</hi> whatſoeuer become of the gift, or the worke, the <hi>fruit</hi> ſhall remaine to <hi>further our Reckoning,</hi> if it be done with a godly purpoſe and for the glory of God.</p>
            <p>But another doubt there is, that <note place="margin">2 Doubt.</note> when ſuch as the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> bad and ſuperſtitious people, haue beene once poſſeſſors of ſuch <hi>wels</hi> and <hi>monuments,</hi> prouided by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Patriarchs, like Iacob:</hi> how men Religious may <hi>vſe</hi> them againe, ſeeing <hi>they</hi> were heathens, who v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually dedicated their <hi>wels</hi> to <hi>Gods and Goddeſſes.</hi> Howſoeuer this <hi>Well</hi> had bin abuſed, our <hi>bleſſed Sauiour</hi> (wee behold) <hi>ſitteth by it,</hi> &amp; asketh <hi>water</hi> at it. Now let mee bee bold before this <hi>high preſence,</hi> (paſſing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3646:39"/> by the free <hi>vſe</hi> of ciuill things graunted euen with <hi>Idolaters,)</hi> to goe further and ſuppoſe our <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Chappels, the tithes</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Religion, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, to be <hi>wels</hi> and <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> that were ſometimes in the hands of <hi>Idolaters,</hi> polluted and defiled by their Corruptions. Is it not lawfull for vs to vſe them in the ſeruice of God, vpon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie? Can we doubt this; ſeeing we vſe the <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſtin. ep. 154.</note> 
               <hi>ſame fountaines, the ſame aire, that hath beene polluted, with I dolatrous ſacrifices, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe offered to Diuels.</hi> Yea ſeeing the <hi>Temples</hi> and other Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, <note place="margin">ib.</note> that haue beene prophaned by Idolatrie, <hi>may</hi> we imploy, <hi>not indeed to priuate vſes, for couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but unto a publike benefit, for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ib.</note> the honour of God euen as men, when they are conuerted from being ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and impious perſons to the true
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3646:40"/> Religion, are to imploie themſelues and their members to ſerue the Lord: I <note place="margin">ibid.</note> ſpeake out of Saint Austen. Saint Paule did eate and drinke &amp; conuerſe <note place="margin">ibid.</note> in Athens a Citie conſecrated to <note n="c" place="margin">Quia Ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas erat Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua eiuſih numini conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crata. Acts 17. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua</hi> an <hi>heathniſh Goddeſſe,</hi> and hee <hi>ſailed in a</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 28. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſhippe hauing the badge of Castor and Pollux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſauiour vouchſafed to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the <hi>Temple,</hi> after it had been prophaned, and <hi>that Temple</hi> which <hi>Herod</hi> had <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſepbus lib. 15.</hi>
               </note> reedified for populer vaine glory; nether did he (that did al things well) forbeare to imploie the <note n="f" place="margin">Iohn 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>water pots</hi> of the <hi>Iewiſh and ſuperstitious purification,</hi> in the work of his gracious miracle. This am I bould to ſpeake, for their ſakes, that are in no liking with aunciently built Churches, and make a maine point of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, either not to enter into <hi>them,</hi> or not to call them by the former names of <hi>ſaints, Saint Peter, Saint</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3646:40"/> 
               <hi>Paul, Saint Alban;</hi> that firſt for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, the ſcripture vſeth the names of <note n="g" place="margin">Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s 28. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Caſtor and Poilux, falſe Gods</hi> without ſcruple: and the Churches of all ages, haue beene content in the tranſlation of the words of the Lord in <note n="h" place="margin">Iob. 38. Amos 5. 8. <hi>Giegor. Mag: in Job. 58.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iob,</hi> and in the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> to vſe the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh appellations of the <hi>ſtarres, Pleiades, Orion, Acturus,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they had fabulous and poeticall Originals. So that, if the names were worſe, then thoſe of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> a well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Conſcience, might vtter them for diſtinction ſake without offence. But now ſeeing they are the Names of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> to whom although as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors and <hi>tutelar Gods,</hi> wee dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate no Churches, nor offer ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication or ſeruice, yet for their vertues and victorious ſufferings, we may loue them, rehearſe their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3646:41"/> names with Reuerence, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their faithfulneſſe. It is not with vs as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Bellar: de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. triumph.</note> obiect, that with <note n="k" place="margin">D. Reinald: de Ro: eccl. l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol: lib. 1. c. 8. §. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Euſtathius</hi> we deteſt all <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and eſpecially thoſe that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the names of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and like onely Conuenticles in priuate? or that with the <hi>Eunomians,</hi> we refuſe to goe into the Churches intitled with the names of <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs?</hi> This may be the fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall whiſpering of ſome wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring houſe-creeper, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of ſome ſeduced ſeparatiſt, but <hi>Wee,</hi> that is, <hi>Dauid</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> our <hi>preists</hi> and people, frequent thoſe <hi>howſes</hi> of <hi>praier,</hi> call them by their former names, enter into them willingly, hauing antiquity, and all reformed Churches for our precedents to do the like. For who knowes not that the Citie, &amp; <hi>Vniuerſitie</hi> of <hi>Geneua</hi> haue their cheif Church retaining the name of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3646:41"/> 
               <hi>Saint Peter,</hi> one intituled <hi>Saint Magdalen, another Saint Geruaſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biſprá.</note> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> whither they vſually reſort to <note n="l" place="margin">Zanch: in 4. praec: to this purpoſe.</note> 
               <hi>holy</hi> exerciſes. Neither is it altogether vaine, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> here in this place, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that ſame <hi>Iacobs well,</hi> which the <hi>Samaritans</hi> ſo named and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before him, making no queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion but that <hi>Iacob</hi> had digged it, although the tradition came from the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Nay our <hi>bleſſed Sauiour</hi> is not ſcrupulous to reſt himſelfe at this <hi>Well,</hi> or to graunt it for <hi>Iacobs,</hi> howſoeuer (which is for our example) he will not be drawne, by the <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>titles of Iacob,</hi> to <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 4. 22.</note> 
               <hi>approue</hi> of a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfcit Religion, wherefore let vs leaue curioſitie in ſuch ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and conclude this point, firſt, with <hi>praiſe</hi> to the Lord that theſe <hi>wels,</hi> theſe <hi>Monuments</hi> and other benefits for the furtherance of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3646:42"/> Religion, ſometimes in poſſeſſion of <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and the ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and by them corrupted and made vnholſome, are againe ſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reſtored, that now we may draw and drinke our fill in them, euen of the pure Riuers of the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life.</hi> Secondly, if it ſhould be proued, that any of theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents were founded &amp; erected by the <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> yet then wee muſt acknowledge our ſelues, much bound to <hi>God,</hi> that wee may drinke of the <note n="n" place="margin">Dent. 6. 11.</note> 
               <hi>wels wee digged not, dwel in houſes that wee builded not,</hi> inioy theſe <hi>Churches,</hi> which wee prepared not, as <note n="o" place="margin">Ludolph:</note> 
               <hi>Noah had the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of that Arke, which was framed by prophane ſhipwrights,</hi> and <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was <hi>refreſhed</hi> with <hi>ſweet hony out of the dead Lion,</hi> that liuing would haue killed him; So that we may ſay with <hi>Samſon,</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iudg. 14. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the ſtrong came ſweet, and out of the</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3646:42"/> 
               <hi>deuowrer came meat.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> But here mee thinks the <hi>Romiſh Samaritans</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt vs, and firſt obiect, that our <hi>faith</hi> buildes no Churches, <hi>digges</hi> no ſuch <hi>wels:</hi> but their Religion, their <hi>Pater noſter</hi> (as they call it) founded all. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Secondly, they lay claime to our <hi>Churches,</hi> nay bragge that themſelues are the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Monuments</hi> and names of godly men, that were ſometimes <hi>pillars</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1. to the 1. ob.</label> To the firſt, whereas they ſay, we <hi>build</hi> no <hi>Churches,</hi> doe no ſuch workes, but they haue beene all the doers, and are ſo ſtill: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere briefly that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>firſt Martyrs,</hi> who planted the Church, did build no materiall <hi>temples,</hi> and yet they are worthily ſtiled <note n="q" place="margin">Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>entinus</note> 
               <hi>Religioſiſ simi mortales,</hi> moſt Religious men, none being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to them ſince. They as the former planters of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3646:43"/> and built vp the people of God, <note n="r" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>as temples for the holy ghoſt to dwell in, vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Chriſt Ieſus being the head corner ſtone,</hi> and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted peace, wealth, opportunitie, and the fauour of <hi>Princes</hi> to erect any Churches and houſes of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, either publike or coſtly. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2. to the 1. ob.</label> 
               <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> more largely I anſwere, that when the Lord vouchſafed, to call <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, then by their Authoritie, and out of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance, they in the profeſsion of <hi>our</hi> Religion, of <hi>Aedes ſacras,</hi> (ſacred houſes) erected <hi>Baſilicas, Kinglike palaces,</hi> thereby the more to honour God with their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and prouide for the more conueniencie of holie Aſſemblies. Now theſe firſt <hi>honorable founders,</hi> were not of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, for they did not vſe ſuch Iewiſh
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3646:43"/> and heathniſh Ceremonies in their <note n="s" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. eccl. lib. 10. c. 3</note> 
               <hi>Church-dedications,</hi> nor ſuch Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or adoration of Saints or Images, as the Romane Church hath ſince brought in. This plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth by the example of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and by the beſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, who, with <hi>Saint Auſten, ſpeake thus like Proteſtants:</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Auguſtin: de Ciuit dei lib. 8 c. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>We or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine no Churches, no Prieſthoods, no rites nor ſacrifices vnto Martyrs, we do not crie at the altars, O Peter, O Paul, O Cyprian, wee offer vnto thee our oblation: but at their Memorials we offer to God, who made them men, and Martyrs, giuing thanks for their victories, and incouraging our ſelues by calling vpon God, to the like Crownes of Martyrdome.</hi> And his is our Religion iuſt; for although we are content to preſerue the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> where they haue ſuffered and are buried, yet it is not to <hi>call</hi> vpon them, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3646:44"/> their conſtancy to the <hi>praiſe of God,</hi> and imitate their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, as occaſion is offered. In which ſence wee are bold to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Reuerent Remembrance in this place, of our <hi>prime-martyr Saint Alban,</hi> by the loſſe of whoſe life, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> firſt made entrie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this lande: <hi>inſomuch</hi> as I may call this place, the <note n="u" place="margin">Oſe: 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>vallie of Achor,</hi> the <hi>doore of hope,</hi> and the <hi>firſt-fruits of England</hi> in ſuffering for the faith.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>3. to the 1. ob.</label> Thirdlie wee anſwer that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee did build no Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches now, (which is vntrue) yet is it no leſſe honorable to bee <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> then <hi>founders. Deucalion</hi> was thought to haue done as great an act, as <hi>Prometheus: Noah</hi> is as much reuowned as <hi>Adam;</hi> and it pleaſed the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> to be a <hi>reſtorer of mankind,</hi> which is a greater title, then to bee the firſt Author, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3646:44"/> was. I am ſure that the worke of our <hi>Redemption,</hi> excelleth our <hi>Creation,</hi> and therefore it is true, that we <note n="*" place="margin">Plus debe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pro me refecto quam facto: Barn: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract: de dilig deo.</note> 
               <hi>owe to the Lord more for our ſelues reformed, then firſt formed. loſias was bleſſed for purging the Temple: Zorobabel</hi> for reedifying the ſame, as well as <hi>Salomon,</hi> who <hi>builded</hi> it. Other former Princes, &amp; great Men, haue brought forth, as firſt Parents, theſe and ſuch like Monuments, which in proceſſe of time had more feeding then tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and therefore grew out of faſhion: But it is the honor of our Religious Kings and Princes, as principally they are nurcing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers of the Goſpell, ſo to draw their breaſts, and ſuckle theſe and ſuch like Orphan-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that by their Princely boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they may be neceſſary and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorie helpes to Gods ſeruice. In naturall children the chiefe care is,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3646:45"/> or ought to be, of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the next of the <hi>body:</hi> firſt <hi>nurture</hi> is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, then <hi>Nature:</hi> and ſo in theſe <hi>Monuments,</hi> chiefly Religion is to be regarded, then the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: firſt muſt a Church be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in <note n="x" place="margin">Barn:</note> 
               <hi>moribus,</hi> then <hi>in marruori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> in manners, then in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and other Ornaments. And this is the courſe of our Religious Princes, firſt to cleanſe theſe <hi>houſes of prayer,</hi> from <hi>Corruption,</hi> &amp; then to raiſe them from their <hi>Ruines.</hi> I may ſpeake ſenſiblie, &amp; if it pleaſe God effectually, in reſpect of <hi>this place,</hi> this auncient, and now droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Church,</hi> vnder whoſe roofe we notwithſtanding are happily preſent before <hi>the Lord,</hi> and his annointed <hi>Iacob.</hi> Neuer did poore <hi>Orphan-Church,</hi> ſtanding in ſuch need of a <hi>royall nurcing father,</hi> more ſeaſonably inioy the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence of ſo great a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3646:45"/> And aboue all, this benefit <hi>ſhee</hi> doth with other her ſiſter <hi>Churches</hi> alreadie enioy, and muſt euer, with all thankefulneſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that by her <hi>royall Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs meanes</hi> (next vnder God,) her children may dayly drinke of <hi>the water of life,</hi> ſucke at the breaſts of our <hi>ſweet Sauiour</hi> here offered, and receaue the comforts of publike praier, of the <hi>Miniſterie</hi> and <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> being the moſt eſſentiall parts of a <hi>Church,</hi> and benefits, as much exceeding the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent building of lime and ſtone, as the pure ſpring water exceeds the workemanſhippe about the <hi>well:</hi> and ſuch as our forefathers would haue reioiced to enioy, in <hi>fields, in woods, m Cottages.</hi> But yet ſeeing this <hi>Monument,</hi> this <hi>building</hi> is now the <hi>place,</hi> the <hi>pallace,</hi> the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Geneſ 36. 22</note> 
               <hi>Rehoboth,</hi> a large <hi>well</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, and roome enough, where
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3646:46"/> where the ſeruants of God doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble for <hi>water</hi> of comfort, it pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth them to ſee the worke of it ſo ruinous, the <hi>brinke</hi> ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, the <hi>ſteening</hi> falne in, and a <hi>Monument,</hi> thus venerable, vpon the waſt, ſo that all that paſſe by are ready to ſpoile her, both the Rich couetous, and the poore irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, both in deſire ſacrilegious: In regard whereof, ſometimes her <hi>ſonnes</hi> doe wiſh that <hi>ſhee</hi> were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <note n="z" place="margin">Auguſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Zacheus,</hi> with a <hi>ſound bodie,</hi> then <hi>Goliah,</hi> with this crazie, hecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Conſumption: becauſe her <hi>paralyticque</hi> members (as a great body vnſound) rather burthen, then beautifie; and yet the reſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and cutting off, of an <hi>Integrall</hi> part, euen in the greateſt body, is a maime and diſfiguring, neither e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vſed, but as <hi>vltimum refugium,</hi> in diſeaſes deſperate. It is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle of much remorſe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3646:46"/> a <hi>noble perſonage,</hi> high-borne, ſo in diſtreſle, that for want of friends and meanes to ſupport <hi>her,</hi> ſhee is ready to <hi>fall,</hi> and lie on the ground, as ſubiect to beggerie, ſcorne and ſhame. Euen <note n="a" place="margin">2 King 9. 34.</note> 
               <hi>King Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu,</hi> had commiſeration <hi>in extremis</hi> vpon <hi>Ieſabel, quia filia Regis,</hi> becauſe ſhee was the <hi>daughter</hi> to a <hi>King,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a <note n="b" place="margin">1 King. 16. 31 daughter: to E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>aal K. of the <hi>Zidomans.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>wicked daughter</hi> of a <hi>heathniſh King.</hi> And may not I cal this Church, a Kings daughter, and in that reſpect looke for pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to whom <note n="c" place="margin">M. Cambden:</note> 
               <hi>Off a a King Chriſtian,</hi> gaue the firſt <hi>being,</hi> &amp; other <note n="d" place="margin">Egfrid: Elbel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Henric. 1. manuſcr. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt.</note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> after him, this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpicuous Ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? Shee hath already met <hi>with Iehu,</hi> who hauing ſeuerely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed her for all the <hi>fornications and witchcraftes;</hi> the Idolatries and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Fryars,</hi> wrought in her, could not chuſe, but now, if he beheld it, remorſe her humble eſtate, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3646:47"/> ſhee is <hi>filia regis,</hi> and <hi>Baſilica, a Kings daughter.</hi> But <hi>Iehu</hi> tooke pittie when it was too late, and when <hi>Ieſabel</hi> was almoſt <hi>deuoured of the dogges:</hi> This Church is yet more happie, who though ſhee hath had many <hi>blowes,</hi> yet hauing not receaued her deathes <hi>wound,</hi> ſhee ſtands capable of the mercie and fauour of a <hi>peaceable Salomon,</hi> a <hi>bleſſed Ioſias,</hi> a <hi>Kingly Iacob,</hi> to giue her life and <hi>health</hi> againe. And it is no ordinary helpe, nor vulgar hand, that can heale her <hi>ſore,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as ſhee was the <hi>daughter,</hi> and is the <hi>nurce-child</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> ſo her diſeaſe is the <hi>Kings euill,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the ſpeedie aſſiſtance of a moſt <hi>Catholike</hi> and <hi>Imperiall Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to cure her wounds, or els his ſacred Authority (if her eſtate bee found deſperate) to cut of her <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified limmes,</hi> and binde vp the ſounder parts for <hi>Gods ſeruice.</hi> Yet
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3646:47"/> it is indeed the Recouerie of her priſtinate health and ſoundneſſe, that her <hi>ſonnes</hi> on their <hi>knees</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: (which if it may not bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained) their <hi>laſt Refuge</hi> and next Petition muſt be (that which <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princes</hi> doe not loue to heare) <note n="e" place="margin">Iſai. 3. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Ruina haec ſub manu tua:</hi> Let her fall be vnder the hand of higheſt Authoritie: being the mournefull note of people when they had <hi>no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reſpondebit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens non ſum medicus ib.</note> 
               <hi>King to helpe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who am I, that I ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into particulars, before my <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>King?</hi> I confeſſe with <hi>St. Barnard,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">De conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras: lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt meae humilitatis dictare ſic autſic faciendum:</hi> It ſtands not with the meaneneſſe of my place to preſcribe this, or that to be done. Yet this let me be bold to ſpeake, that the <hi>ſunne giues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and luſtre,</hi> where it <hi>ſhines: foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> make barren grounds <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> where they paſſe along: Our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3646:48"/> 
               <hi>ſweet Sauiour,</hi> both the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>fountaine of truth,</hi> ment ſome good to the <hi>place</hi> and <hi>perſons,</hi> when hee went tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſate at <hi>Iacobs well:</hi> and who knowes, what our moſt <hi>Royall and Religious Iacob</hi> may intend for <hi>vs,</hi> ſeeing <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. King. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>reſt on euerie ſide (as to Salomon</hi> when he built the <hi>Temple,) and there is neither aduerſarie, nor euill to reſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>4. to the 1. ob.</label> But againe, me thinkes, I heare the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> (who like <hi>Sanbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi> and his Confedcrates deſpiſe our building,) mock at our hopes, as Idle and fruſtiate, becauſe theſe are no daies, to build or repaire Churches, or doe ſuch like works, <hi>as they ſay.</hi> In further anſwere to theſe deceitfull workers and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, let me be bold a little to <hi>boaſt</hi> our <hi>faith</hi> in this point, which hath not beene ſo <hi>Lame</hi> nor <hi>idle</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3646:48"/> in the workes of <hi>Charitie</hi> and <hi>pietie,</hi> as they reproch vs. Let our chiefe <hi>Citie London</hi> ſpeake to the praiſe of <hi>God,</hi> and the Iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our faith by ſuch workes: Nay let her onely ſhowe, what <note n="h" place="margin">M. D. Willet.</note> 
               <hi>three Hoſpitals</hi> of incomparable foundation and prouiſion for <note n="i" place="margin">1. Chriſts hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall.</note> 
               <hi>friendleſſe children,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 St. Thomas hoſpitall.</note> 
               <hi>Impotent people,</hi> and <note place="margin">3 Bridewell.</note> 
               <hi>inor dinate walkers,</hi> ſhee enioieth by the happie Raigne of that truely vertuous <hi>King Ed: the ſixt,</hi> of bleſſed memori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>: beſides many other prouiſions daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing towards the comfort of priſoners, mainteinance of the poore, and miniſterie. Let thoſe two. glorious <hi>Eyes</hi> of our Engliſh <hi>body,</hi> the <hi>two fountains</hi> of Learning and Religion, <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> vtter their knowledge, what the <hi>light</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> hath done for them, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of <hi>not</hi> many <hi>yeares.</hi> Our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:3646:49"/> 
               <hi>Oxford</hi> might claime for the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the foundations, or the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing or eſtabliſhment of her <note n="i" place="margin">See <hi>Crowly.</hi> Try and then truſt.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt-Church, her Trinity Colledge,</hi> and <hi>St. Iohns,</hi> as ſhee doth for her <hi>Ieſus Colledge:</hi> But ſhee cannot but ſpeake her Ioy for her Copious and excellent <hi>Librarie,</hi> her Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>ſchoole</hi> ſo adorned, ſo augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, her <hi>Waddam Colledge,</hi> newlie founded, richly prouided for, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faire <hi>Enlargements</hi> in the moſt Colledges, in buildings, Exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and domeſticall Libraries, for the furtherance of the <hi>ſonnes of the Prophets.</hi> Neither may I forget, the new life, <hi>which Oriall Colledge, when ſhee was almoſt at the laſt gaſpe, and on the hazard, receaued by the royall Charter and</hi> Confirmation of our <hi>euer-bleſſed Iacob,</hi> at his firſt enterance. This and much more may <hi>Oxford</hi> ſpeake to <hi>Gods glorie;</hi> and the other ſiſter <hi>Cambridge</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:3646:49"/> ſpeaketh as much in many points. Shee hath brought forth her <hi>Twinnes,</hi> her <hi>Emanuel</hi> and her <hi>Sid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Colledges.</hi> Shee may demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to the honor of the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> many <hi>Cels</hi> conuerted into one glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>houſe</hi> of Learning and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo beautified, and repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that it ſeemes to bee the <hi>Via lactea</hi> of that Vniuerſitie, where there is a <hi>Concurrency</hi> of many <hi>ſtarres,</hi> ſhining together as in the <hi>firmament.</hi> Neither may <hi>ſhee</hi> bee ſilent of her <hi>Saint Iohns,</hi> which daielie groweth from a <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to a <hi>flood,</hi> the <hi>head</hi> whereof not willing to bee knowne to the world, but the Aboundance is from <hi>God</hi> thorough the fruit of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to the onely <hi>glorie</hi> of <hi>his</hi> name. But it is both hard, and beſide my purpoſe to make an exact <hi>Catalogue</hi> of all thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Monuments,</hi> of the late foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3646:50"/> increaſings and Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments within thoſe <hi>ſacred Nurce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> And who can reckon vp the <hi>Almeshouſes, hoſpitals, freeſchooles,</hi> and other beneficiall and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Prouiſions</hi> for the <hi>people of God,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> ſeruice, through the whole Land, euen vnder the <hi>Goſpell?</hi> I ſhould forget my ſelfe, if I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred not, that this place is not without a freeſchoole, as a <hi>little ſpring,</hi> where youth may drinke <hi>in,</hi> the <hi>firſt licour</hi> of wholſomlearning, flowing from the bounty of a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Princeſſe,</hi> now with <hi>God,</hi> by the Mediation of that worthie <hi>Lord Keeper, Bacon;</hi> ſo much hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> If I ſhould be ſilent, the late <note n="k" place="margin">Statute ann 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Iacobi Re gis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſtatutes</hi> would tell you of that royall <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs Colledge,</hi> newly founded, and dailie increaſing, for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſacred ſtudies, &amp; deepeeſt learning. And the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3646:50"/> proclaimeth thoſe worthy <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> partly written by an <note n="l" place="margin">Apolog. pro Iuram: fidel. praeſat. moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note> 
               <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall</hi> hand, partly by <note n="m" place="margin">Biſhop Iewel. Wincheſter. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. D. Keinald: D. Whitac. D. Fulke. D. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot. D. Field. D. Moorton. D. Hacwill. my L. Cooke: many others.</note> 
               <hi>learned ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,</hi> for the <hi>mainteinance</hi> of true <hi>Religion</hi> againſt falſhood and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: I need not ſpeak of them. The Northern borderes praiſe <hi>God</hi> for that Kingly worke, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their Church in <hi>Arthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret:</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Bath,</hi> which long ſtood naked and bare, is rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cloathed by the bounty of a right <note n="n" place="margin">L. B. of Bath &amp; Wels.</note> 
               <hi>Reuerend and Religious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Virginian Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> can witneſſe how willing our royall <hi>Iacob</hi> is to propagate the <hi>Goſpell</hi> together with ciuilitie and trades: And daily beholding a gracious <hi>King ſo</hi> forward, and <hi>ſo</hi> many worthy <hi>ſubiects,</hi> ſtirred vp by his <hi>example; Quid non ſpere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus?</hi> What good thing is there, but wee may expect? Wherefore our aduerſaries cannot ſay, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3646:51"/> our <hi>faith</hi> is altogether <hi>Idle,</hi> in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or repairing Monuments of this Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>5 to the 1 ob.</label> But yet againe let me be bold to retire, for ſome weakelings ſake, who deeming the former foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Erectors of Churches, ſo farre peerleſſe, crie out with the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> when they behold ſuch <hi>Monuments</hi> as this: Behold what <note n="o" place="margin">Marke 13. 1.</note> 
               <hi>goodly buildings of old!</hi> Be pleaſed therefore to take notice, what wee can ſay for this, not in <hi>enuie</hi> to our <hi>Auncients,</hi> but in <hi>loue</hi> to the truth. Our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Princes, and People, were long in gathering <hi>ſtones</hi> together, and now at one inſtant the <hi>Romiſh fauourites</hi> ſhewe vs great <hi>heapes</hi> pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>vp,</hi> without mentioning with what leaſure and diſtance of time they were gathered together: as though <hi>Rome</hi> had beene builded <hi>all</hi> in a day. This <hi>Church</hi> may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3646:51"/> ſeeme <note n="p" place="margin">Ecleſia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi operis. Beda.</note> 
               <hi>a wonderfull peece of worke</hi> to the beholders: yet when it ſhall be vnderſtood, that it had many <hi>Kings,</hi> ſucceſſiuely founders, many <hi>rich Contributors,</hi> manie <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eldred, Ead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Poulus, Ricard. Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes de Cetta, Willm. Hugo, Michael, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> Abbots.</note> 
               <hi>fat Abbots and Priors, Benefactors</hi> for manie yeeres, beſide the <hi>ranſacking</hi> of the <hi>olde Citie Veru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am,</hi> to aduance it, and that it was at the leaſt <hi>foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeeres</hi> before it was perfected, and then but of a rude bricke nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and after againe the bricke about to be turned into <hi>marble,</hi> &amp; <note place="margin">Ioannes Stilb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach, prior. Manuſcript. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cox.</note> ſo neuer finiſhed neither (for <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent opera interrupta,</hi> the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip remaineth but abruptly ſtill, as the pillars witneſſe:) then is the wonder not ſo great, and we well perceaue, that ſuperſtition in the greateſt heate had <note n="r" place="margin">Sub Will. Ab. 22. ſiontale huius eccl. te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioſam moram traxerat.</note> 
               <hi>tardiora molimina,</hi> ſlower progreſſes; longer trauaile, and not ſo quicke deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as they would make vs belieue. But <hi>Date creſcendi copiam:</hi> Let the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3646:52"/> Lord giue <hi>leaue,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and proſperitie to our religious <hi>Princes,</hi> &amp; then after ſuch diſtance of time, let the Aduerſaries call vs to a reckoning, what <hi>fruits</hi> our <hi>faith</hi> hath produced. Now be pleaſed to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber then in briefe, and lay altogether: <hi>firſt</hi> that the <hi>primitiue Chriſtians</hi> fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no Churches, for want of <hi>meanes</hi> &amp; <hi>opportunity,</hi> yet they did buiid vp the <hi>Church</hi> of God with their <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> with their <hi>liues,</hi> and blood, and ſo did our <hi>Religious</hi> Forefathers vnder perſecution. <hi>Secondly</hi> that the <hi>firſt founders,</hi> who beganne to erect Churches, were of our <hi>faith,</hi> and not of the moderne <hi>Romiſh</hi> profeſſion. <hi>Thirdly</hi> that it is as honorable, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten more neceſſary to repaire thoſe <hi>Monuments,</hi> then to build <hi>them</hi> at the firſt. <hi>Fourthlie,</hi> that our <hi>faith</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning freedome vnder religious <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> hath been Actiue &amp; Aboundant in good works for neceſſarie purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3646:52"/> 
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> that thoſe great <hi>Monuments</hi> which our Aduerſaries boaſt of, had a longer time to their accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then they would haue vs ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine: And in regard of <hi>theſe</hi> premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thoſe worke-vaunters haue no ſuch great aduantage ouer our faith in founding and building, as they would make the world beleeue.</p>
            <p>One thing more I obſerued, which <note place="margin">2. Ob.</note> is, that as the Romaniſts lay claim to our Churches, ſo they intitle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the Catholike Church it ſelfe, pretending that they are vndoubted heires and ſucceſſors of all Ancient founders. And as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> pleaded, that they were the true worſhippers, &amp; <hi>Iacobs</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, becauſe they had <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> whereof <hi>he</hi> dranke; the <hi>mount</hi> where <hi>hee</hi> worſhipped: ſo they haue the names of <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; the <hi>places,</hi> where perhaps <hi>they</hi> preached &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered; they talke of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3646:53"/> 
               <hi>Martyrs,</hi> of the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councels,</hi> they ingroſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the name <hi>Church &amp; Catholike,</hi> yea they haue the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as the <hi>Iewes</hi> had, in their <hi>bookes;</hi> or as the <note n="s" place="margin">Iudges 16.</note> 
               <hi>Philiſtins</hi> had <hi>Samſon,</hi> in captiuitie, fettered, ſhaued &amp; blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. But ſhall we beleeue that they are the only Catholikes &amp; Children of the Apoſtles, for theſe <hi>probabilities</hi> and preſumptions? Or that they are the onely ſpouſe of Chriſt, becauſe they ſhew the <note n="t" place="margin">Mr. White, out of Jſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: pref.</note> 
               <hi>ſheathes,</hi> and <hi>Caskets</hi> where the <hi>Ornaments and Iewels of the husband once lay?</hi> Or becauſe like the <hi>madde-man</hi> in <hi>Athenaeus,</hi> they take an Inuentory of all <hi>goods</hi> in the Church for their <hi>own;</hi> as <hi>he</hi> did in all ſhips that arriued there, are they the right ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? It is not ſheepes clothing that transformes the <hi>wolfe,</hi> nor the Lions <hi>skinne</hi> that alters the Aſſes Nature. They are not therfore right Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; good Catholikes, that boaſt of names and titles, Places and Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3646:53"/> no more then <note n="u" place="margin">Dion. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeus.</note> 
               <hi>Vibius Rufus was a good Orator</hi> for <hi>hauing Ciceroes wife:</hi> or a <hi>great Emperour</hi> for hauing <hi>Caeſars ſaddle:</hi> or that <hi>fooliſh</hi> ſmatterer a <note n="*" place="margin">Lucian.</note> 
               <hi>good Philoſopher,</hi> who ſtudied by <hi>Epictetus his Candleſticke:</hi> or <note n="x" place="margin">Fox con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra: Oſor.</note> 
               <hi>Nean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi> the <hi>Iangler,</hi> a good Muſician, for carrying the <hi>harp of Orpheus.</hi> Nay the <hi>Samaritans</hi> ſeemed on a better grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ſome things then the Romaniſts; for they indeed had <hi>Iacobs Well:</hi> but theſe obtrude vnto vs, <hi>Reliques</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> which are but meere <hi>Impoſtures</hi> and <hi>for geries.</hi> Their vſurping <hi>Prelate</hi> muſt be <hi>Chriſts Vicar, Saint Peters ſucceſſor,</hi> when he ſucceeds him, but as <note n="y" place="margin">Mr. D. K. ex Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anz:</note> 
               <hi>night</hi> doth <hi>the day, a tempeſt a calme, ſickenes health:</hi> Yet his <note n="z" place="margin">D. R. Conference.</note> prerogatiue muſt be <hi>Peters,</hi> his dignity <hi>Peters,</hi> his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <hi>Peters,</hi> his robes and royalties <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> his Ring <hi>Peters,</hi> his ſea <hi>Peters,</hi> his keyes <hi>Peters,</hi> his pence <hi>Peters.</hi> And as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> ſaid, <hi>Iacob gaue vs this</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:3646:54"/> 
               <hi>Well:</hi> ſo <hi>they ſay, Chriſt</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> or the <hi>Emperor</hi> gaue vs theſe <hi>wels,</hi> this <hi>honor,</hi> theſe <hi>crowns, theſe promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> So poore <hi>Peter</hi> hath <hi>rich heyres:</hi> And this is the <hi>Gorgons head,</hi> which aſtoniſhed the world a long time; <note n="a" place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſed vltra a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient: They ſhal preuail nolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, for their madnes ſhal be made manifeſt to all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we leaue theſe ſeducing &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to ſee their <hi>errors,</hi> if it pleaſe the <hi>Lord,</hi> &amp; with the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> to bee conuerted to the ſound knowledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour.</hi> And I returne to our ſelues, to whom the Lord hath giuen now the poſſeſſion of <hi>I acobs Wel,</hi> the vſe of many tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and ſpirituall <hi>benefits</hi> to further vs in his ſeruice, if we take our opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. For firſt our <hi>God</hi> hath reuealed vnto vs that <hi>rocke &amp; fountaine</hi> of our <hi>ſaluation Chriſt I eſus,</hi> wherein are all our <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 87. 7</note> 
               <hi>freſh ſprings of hope and Comfort,</hi> the knowledg of whom by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tranſlated read, &amp; preached, as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3646:54"/> by ſtreams &amp; Conduits, do continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 46. 4.</note> 
               <hi>glad and refreſh the Citie of God.</hi> And to perpetuate theſe bleſsings, the Lord hath fauoted vs with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, whoſe hart is a <hi>Wel-ſpring</hi> of wiſdome, Counſell &amp; Iuſtice: And ſo bleſſed him while hee drinks the <hi>Water</hi> of his owne <hi>louely Ciſterne,</hi> that thence iſſueth a happy <hi>Riuer</hi> of <hi>Royal Apparent ſucceſsion,</hi> as from a bleſſed <hi>fountaine,</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> grant, may run on, in <hi>grace</hi> &amp; glory, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all true <hi>Chriſtian hearts,</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi> In regard of which ineſtimable fauours, let me be bold, without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the royal patience of my <hi>Lord and King,</hi> to ſpeake a few words, to al the worthy children and ſubiects of our <hi>Princely I acob,</hi> here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled; &amp; ſo I wil conclude. Seeing the <hi>Lord</hi> hath granted vs to reap the fruit of many fauours, ſowed by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Benefactors of al ſorts, &amp; <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 66. 12.</note> hath <hi>extended peace ouer vs as a flood,</hi> &amp; the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3646:55"/> Goſpell as a <hi>flowing ſtreame:</hi> Seeing the true <hi>faith</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto vs not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary &amp; <hi>alone,</hi> but accompained with infinite bleſſings; ſo that we haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and encouragement from the higheſt Authority to do good, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny opportunities to effect the ſame: let vs be ready to ſhew forth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward fountaine of our <hi>faith,</hi> by the outward ſtreams of our <hi>Loue.</hi> Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally do <hi>Yee,</hi> the moſt eminent in note, indeuor to do moſt good, whoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate <hi>wels</hi> are anſwerable to your <hi>wils,</hi> &amp; ſubſtance to your deſire; Let ſome <hi>water</hi> of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort flow from you, to the <note place="margin">Putei dum bauriuntur ſpecioſiores ſuns. Baſil.</note> publike benefit of the <hi>Church &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. They that would haue their wels to be wholſome, do draw them ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and ye that would haue your riches bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, muſt diſtribute them often.</hi> Thinke what <hi>Oceans</hi> of wealth run ouer the back-in <hi>weeds &amp; ſhreds,</hi> and thorough the throat in <hi>puddle,</hi> &amp; <hi>pamper;</hi> how much is waſted by many, in vaine
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3646:55"/> pleaſures, priuate buildings, fruitleſſe exerciſes; by others in ſuperſtitious &amp; Idolatrous Aduancements: &amp; turne ſome of the ſtreames of your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines at laſt, into the <hi>barren fields of the poore,</hi> and to the watering of the <hi>Sanctuarie.</hi> Paſſe not thorough the world as <hi>arrowes through the aire,</hi> and <hi>ſhips thorough the ſea,</hi> leauing no mark nor trace behind you; vnlade the weight of your burdens, that your reckoning may be the lighter: <hi>Heere</hi> and euerie <hi>where</hi> are <hi>hauens,</hi> to eaſe your Iourney, &amp; ſpeed your arriuall towards heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let not <hi>Leah</hi> reproch <hi>Rachel</hi> for barrenneſſe, nor <hi>blinde</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition reprooue our <hi>Religion</hi> for lameneſſe. Let vs <hi>trie it out</hi> with our Aduerſaries by action, as well as by profeſsion; <hi>Spectemur agendo.</hi> They wrought for their own ſakes, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of merit; Let vs worke for Gods ſake in regard of duty. Can ye not <hi>build</hi> Churches? yet repaire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3646:56"/> Can yee not <hi>preach</hi> the Goſpell? yet <hi>further</hi> the Goſpel. Can you not build Hoſpitals? Yet refreſh the poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt: when like their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> they ſit hungry, weary, &amp; thirſty by your <hi>Wels.</hi> Trifle not as the <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> did, when Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked water; pretending Religion to ſaue you <hi>purſes,</hi> as the <hi>Samaritan</hi> did to ſaue her <hi>Paines.</hi> In a word let vs be ready <hi>to doe good, to diſtribute</hi> without <hi>murmuring</hi> &amp; <hi>reaſonings</hi> &amp; <hi>Lay up ſtore</hi> and a <hi>good foundation for the time to come,</hi> that we may be the ſons of <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life,</hi> the <hi>giuer of liuing</hi> water; who with his aboundance vouchſafe to make our ſoules, like a <hi>well wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> like a ſpring, whoſe waters faile not: and bleſſe our princely <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> going out and comming in, from this time forth for cuermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3646:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
